<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Camino de Santiago on internet bloggo</title>
    <link>/categories/camino-de-santiago/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Camino de Santiago on internet bloggo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/camino-de-santiago/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>18: Home</title>
      <link>/posts/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/home/</guid>
      <description>After Belgium, I spent one night in Prague and took a bus to Hungary the next morning. I stayed in Budapest for 10 days with Eszter, the Hungarian woman I had a crush on at the beginning of this whole adventure.
It felt strange, to be back in the swing of normalcy, as if such a thing was possible after such a journey.
There was no bitterness or resentment toward Marieke.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17: The Final Goodbye</title>
      <link>/posts/final-goodbye/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/final-goodbye/</guid>
      <description>I arrive in Belgium late in the afternoon. The weather is exceptional: half-clouded skies with no reservation of sunlight, a perfect balance of cool and warm. I exit from the train station and hoist myself against a tall statue, eagerly looking for my squirrelly Belgium. 15 minutes pass before I spot her standing only 20 meters behind me, clad in a gray hoodie and a black leather jacket, lightly faded jeans and the tall leather boots of an amazon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16: Santiago</title>
      <link>/posts/santiago/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/santiago/</guid>
      <description>“How we spend our days is, of course, how we spend our lives.” –Annie Dillard
 October 8, 2017 - Day 31 Pedrouzo, Spain.
In 20 kilometers, I will reach Santiago de Compostela. The anticipation has left me sleepless. Ali and Karen are fast asleep. Hope to see them again soon. I pack my things and make a quiet exit.
It’s dark out. Cars lie dormant under the hazy hue of flickering streetlights.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15: Letters Worth Czeching Out</title>
      <link>/posts/letters-czech/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/letters-czech/</guid>
      <description>I wrote these letters to my friend, Stepan, from the Czech Republic. Including them because they might help to create a better picture of my experience. He had joined M and I a few days before M left. These letters were written afterwards.
September 23, 2017  Hey it&amp;rsquo;s Phil.
I walked to Hontanas yesterday from Burgos (about 30 km). It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful village worth staying at. Today I&amp;rsquo;m walking to Itero de Vega, about 21 km.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14: Letters to a Camino Soulmate</title>
      <link>/posts/letters-soulmate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/letters-soulmate/</guid>
      <description>These are the emails Marieke and I wrote to each other after she was gone. They might give you a better picture of my Camino experience. Writing to her was always a highlight. Sorry for the grammar. Wrote every letter on my phone.
September 21, 2017  I just realized I did not give you my email. Safe travels! Thank you for everything.
–Phil
 September 23, 2017  Yesterday, as I walked away from Burgos, it clicked: you were gone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13: The Iron Cross</title>
      <link>/posts/ironcross/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ironcross/</guid>
      <description>October 1st, 2017 - Day 25 Dawn. A ridge of silhouettes and gray clouds against a colorless expanse. A string of headlamps clambering up a mountain. At the top, an iron cross.
The autumnal air invigorates me, my legs are weightless. I pass several pilgrims on my way up. Shanti is up ahead. I reach him and he smiles at me. We climb through the dark together, delighting in the thrill of the ascent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12: Journal Entries from Day 22 - 24</title>
      <link>/posts/journal22-24/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/journal22-24/</guid>
      <description>September 28, 2017 - Day 22 To be yourself–
Easy to say, hard to do.
What we think is not ours.
What we believe is shaped by others.
The only thing we own is
what we feel.
Our inner compass, the way we connect with
The outer world; only we can see and touch and
Feel the way we do. Never lose it.
Never let it go.

Met Enrico and Sia today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11: A Sea of Stars</title>
      <link>/posts/stars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/stars/</guid>
      <description>Day 21 4:30am. I inch out from my sleeping bag like a slug, careful not to disturb the others in the room, pack my things and head downstairs. Pauline and Morgan are already awake. We’re late.
My eyes are crusty. I wolf down a prepacked sandwich – chorizo and cheese – with yogurt. Pauline makes us some coffee. Bland, but it will do. Shoes on, rucksacks shouldered, we’re on the move.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10: Journal Entries from Day 17 - 20</title>
      <link>/posts/journal17-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/journal17-20/</guid>
      <description>September 23, 2017 - Day 17 We are always on the cusp of collapse and redemption. Do we choose to rise, or do we settle and fall?
Stories = meaning. The mind is a meaning-making machine.
Stories have the power to change people’s lives, and we are the narrators.

Today, a group of Americans invited me to their table at dinner. They were much older than me and asked a lot of questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9: An Ode to the Road</title>
      <link>/posts/ode/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ode/</guid>
      <description>Each and every day I wake and walk with the sun.
It starts low, climbing over hillsides, rising slowly.
It finds its temporary place amid the sky
and begins to color the Meseta.
Front and center a shadow grows.
It looks at me with indifference – a mirror of my darker side.
Fear, insecurity, doubt,
The manifestation of my inner demons.
Each and every day, I wake and walk and confront them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8: Gone</title>
      <link>/posts/gone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/gone/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve sunken into the depths of an all-too-familiar melancholy.
She is gone. I am alone. My emotions swing to the erratic cadence of an unforgiving metronome.
 I’m fine. Tick. I’m fine. Tick. I’m not. Tick. 
I miss the jade of her eyes, those luminescent opals I so often lose myself in. The ease of her smile, always able to bring about my own. The way she plucked those juicy blackberries from their thorny brambles, always a tad out of reach, the hem of her shirt lifting ever so slightly in the process, revealing the contours of a titillating landscape I secretly wished to explore.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7: Goodbye</title>
      <link>/posts/goodbye/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/goodbye/</guid>
      <description>Day 15. We’re sitting amid a small cluster of dining tables in the main plaza of Burgos, sipping on wine and eating tapas. The patrons and pilgrims look happy, the cathedral towers above us. I look up and wonder, is there such a thing as a good goodbye?
Marieke looks content and tells her squirrel joke again. I try to listen, but my attention has been seized by the fact that she is leaving tonight.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6: Sunsets and Soulmates</title>
      <link>/posts/suns-souls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/suns-souls/</guid>
      <description>“Phil! I have a genius idea. You’re really going to like it.”
It&amp;rsquo;s the 12th day. Marieke, Stepan and I go to the top of a hill to catch the sunset. We sift through an amber field of grass and wheat and settle ourselves in a small circular clearing. The sky is cloudless, a cool breeze is present.
We talk for awhile, about what I cant&amp;rsquo;t remember, but I feel wonderfully content.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5: The Cusp of Time and Infinity</title>
      <link>/posts/cusp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cusp/</guid>
      <description>In the morning we walk to Pamplona, our first city. I run into Maria and chat with her for a brief moment before running off with the girls to get breakfast. I didn’t know it then, but that would be my final conversation with her. One thing the Camino teaches you, by nature of necessity, is how to let go. People, places, your past. The present demands it be so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4: Möge die Straße</title>
      <link>/posts/strasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/strasse/</guid>
      <description>Another gray and rainy day. We sleep in and start walking at 8am. After the deep and enlightening conversations of yesterday, we decide to walk in solitude –– together, but left to the vicinity of our inner worlds.
My feelings throughout the morning are in contrast with the highs of the previous; I was in a blue, melancholic state of mind. Thoughts of the future, about something out of reach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3: Tea</title>
      <link>/posts/tea/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/tea/</guid>
      <description>Through the window I see Sun-bathed flowers and untouched rock,
Blades of grass and untrodden walks,
Endless possibility.
I ask of you Time
To yield your determined hand
So I may dance
Forever with Infinity.
 I run into Matilde and Franca while departing from Roncesvalles. They&amp;rsquo;re headed in the opposite direction, back toward the albergue, when they call out to me.
“Phiiiiilll! Heeeey we’re gonna make some tea! Would you like to join us?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2: First Ascent</title>
      <link>/posts/firstascent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/firstascent/</guid>
      <description>I woke to the sound of creaking bunk beds, rustling backpacks, and hushed chatter. 5:30 a.m. Time to go. I put my boots on, packed my sleeping bag, and went downstairs.
Small talk of good weather and stellar walking conditions and free bread as stiff as stones. I devour as much of it as my mouth can muster and head out.
The first day was supposed to be arduous: 27 kilometers from Saint-Jean to Roncesvalles, with a gradual gain of 1400 meters in elevation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1: Beginnings</title>
      <link>/posts/beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/beginnings/</guid>
      <description>The Camino de Santiago is a network of pilgrimage routes that ultimately converge on the city of Santiago de Compostela in Northwestern Spain, where the great Saint James is rumored to be buried.
The most popular route is the Camino Frances. It begins at Saint-Jean-Pied-de-Port in Southern France, a small city located north of the Pyrenees, and totals about 500 miles across Spain to the city of Santiago de Compostela. Many walk the Camino for spiritual and religious reasons; I walked in search of myself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>0: Introduction</title>
      <link>/posts/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/introduction/</guid>
      <description>In May of 2017, while working in a Title I Elementary school in New Hampshire, I read a little fable called “Rebirth” by Kaval Ravikant.
The main character, Amit, is unable to return home after the death of his estranged father. He wanders, lost and filled with pain and grief, and is led to the Camino de Santiago. There he meets many travelers and pilgrims. Some are lost and searching for answers, others are running from their past, but all have a story to share.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>