<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>notes on internet bloggo</title>
    <link>/tags/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in notes on internet bloggo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bearing Witness</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-06-07-bearing-witness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-06-07-bearing-witness/</guid>
      <description>There were 16 of us nestled in the sunlit alcove of the church. I looked at the stranger sitting on a navy-blue cushion before me and wondered what she was thinking about. She smiled at me, and I smiled back. We introduced ourselves and made small talk, as did everyone else and their adjacent stranger. Then the bell chimed, and the room fell into silence.
We turned our gaze to Mike, the PI of the study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pale Blue Dot</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-03-15-pale-blue-dot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-03-15-pale-blue-dot/</guid>
      <description>Propelled into space in 1977, NASA’s scientific objective of launching the Voyager I was to photograph the planets of the outer solar system. They expected the spacecraft to function no further than Saturn. Yet work it did, and it continues to defy expectation up to this day, still traveling at 40,000 miles per hour, somewhere at or beyond the edges of our solar system.
When the Voyager passed Saturn, Carl Sagan – astronomer, cosmologist, astrophysicist, lover and communicator of science – requested that NASA turn the cameras back toward home.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons in Adulthood</title>
      <link>/posts/adulthood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/adulthood/</guid>
      <description>Crossroads My year of service with City Year, New Hampshire was coming to an end. I knew that I didn’t want to become a teacher anymore, but I still liked the idea of shaping the young minds of the future, so I applied to Boston University’s Masters program in Educational Leadership and Policy Studies.
I was waiting for my flight home in O’Hare International Airport when I received the news.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Letters to a Young Scientist</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-08-05-letters-to-a-young-scientist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-08-05-letters-to-a-young-scientist/</guid>
      <description>Veteran biologist and teacher of science Edward Wilson lays out a few principles for the young scientist to keep in mind as he/she/they proceed in their career:
 Put passion ahead of training. Feel out in any way you can what you most want to do in science, or technology, or some other science-related profession. Obey that passion as long as it lasts. Feed it with the knowledge the mind needs to grow.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>