<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>@Nguyenhphil’s internet bloggo - internet bloggo</title>
    <link>//</link>
    <description>All entries in internet bloggo on internet bloggo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 09:50:55 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Blog update</title>
        <link>/microposts/update-theme/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2019 09:50:55 -0400</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/microposts/update-theme/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Updated the theme of my blog! Really digging it, especially the micropost feature. Thanks &lt;a href=&#34;https://themes.gohugo.io/internet-weblog/&#34;&gt;Josh&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Rome</title>
        <link>/posts/2019-06-23-rome/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2019-06-23-rome/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently went to Rome, and it was nothing short of stimulating, sensuous, and overwhelming. From the minimal use of ingredients in Italian cuisine to the incredible works of Michaelangelo and other Roman artists, everywhere you went, everything you touched, tasted and smelled, everything you experienced, it all seemed like some part of a grand plan aimed at steering one’s senses toward a deeper appreciation and understanding of beauty and aesthetics. The city was a living, breathing work of art, an astounding pillar of human ingenuity that left me wide-eyed and dumbstruck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough, it was there that for the first time I felt homesick while traveling. The feeling hit me when my friends and I began imagining what it’d be like to live in Rome. It didn&amp;rsquo;t take long for me to came to the conclusion that I much preferred the quiet and serene nature of Vermont. Rome, as one friend put it, is a zoo. It was loud, constricting, and touristy. Some people may enjoy this kind of environment, but I thrive in smaller cities and places with a more communal feeling. Rome also lacked the particular kind of wilderness that I’ve come to love, find solace in, and be humbled by while living in the green mountain state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a sense of home was a relatively new concept for me. What did it mean to miss home? Perhaps what I missed wasn’t Vermont, but rather the life that I’ve built over the past year and a half. The routines, the familiarity, going to Mag’s cafe to read, work, and write, walking up the Burlington bike path by Champlain lake. The verdancy and birdsong. The numerous dates and unrequited loves. My colleagues who double as my friends. All of this was home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon closer introspection, I also realized I didn&amp;rsquo;t just miss home. I was plagued by restlessness, confusion, uneasiness, and I only had faint clues as to why. The inner home that was showing signs of wear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-past-year&#34;&gt;The Past Year&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Step back a year and I was starting to work on the prerequisite coursework for UVM’s Complex Systems and Data Science graduate program. My original goal in pursuing this program was to continue working on the ABCD Study as a full-fledged researcher, but to also gain an in-demand set of technical skills in case my intentions changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time progressed, it became clear to me that the reality of working in academia was significantly different from how initially imagined it to be. In most cases, academic researchers aren’t obligated to only their research. They also had to apply for grants, cater their papers to specific academic journals, navigate university politics, teach and mentor students, run their own lab, and relentlessly fight for tenure. Not that all of this is undesirable, but it makes the research seem secondary. Maybe it was all worth it for the opportunity to do science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed rational then to find out if I’d actually enjoy doing the research itself. I reached out to my PI and asked if I could work on a research project under my guidance, and she graciously granted me the opportunity. Long story short, I didn’t enjoy it. I bemoaned the literature reviews, academic writing, and how little feedback I received from the work. I never really knew if I was moving in the right direction, and what was deemed a discovery was less than thrilling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I was missing the bigger picture, I thought. They weren&amp;rsquo;t merely hunting for p-values; they were asking and refining questions, proposing and testing hypotheses, defining and advancing science. My optimism was often revived when I reminded myself of this. But when it came to actually doing the work, my mind was often resistant and someplace else. Perhaps I liked the idea of becoming a scientist more than actually being a scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I trudged through and finished the project, but by semester’s end, my thoughts had grown cynical and indifferent as my curiosity and general enthusiasm for science waned. I was likely burning out at this point. In addition to the research project, I was still studying for calculus and statistics while also working full time on the study. A break was called for. And fortunately, we were heading to Rome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;ohbm&#34;&gt;OHBM&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went to Rome not just to travel, but to also attend the 2019 OHBM (Organization for Human Brain Mapping) conference. It was the perfect opportunity to gain some perspective on the field of science, and whether or not I would fit in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I skipped most of the keynotes and lectures, partly out of disinterest, but mainly because I wanted to interact with the scientists themselves. I wanted to learn about their lives and what drove them into academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coincidentally, I spent a lot of time with the graduate students and postdocs who were already in my lab. Beyond the scope of email, small talk, and the tasks I’d offered to help them with, we didn’t talk much or know each other well. Like any other job, they said, being a scientist has its ups and downs. It’s true that the common perception of being a scientist consisted of long hours and an absolute dedication to one’s work. One anecdote involved a woman who was incredibly successful by academic standards, yet it was said that she hadn’t seen her young son in over three months. Apparently he had drawn her a picture and would only show it to her if she came home. I don’t know the full extent of their circumstances, but it seemed like a strange and somewhat disturbing cry for attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, there were also scientists who seemed to lead rich and fulfilling lives outside of academia. Max and Shana, the two postdocs in my lab, said if they couldn’t be successful working an average of 45 hours per week, then academia just wasn’t worth it. They cared about other things too. Of course, they worked their asses off when they had to, but they also knew how to shift gears when progress was no longer being made. “Work hard, play hard” was their motto, which was nice to witness and be a part of in the various outings we had in Rome. It painted a different picture of what a scientist could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I presented my poster on the third day of the conference. I was a bit nervous because I knew there were some shortcomings in my methods, but it was good practice to show my work, and I received great feedback from kind postdocs and graduate students. Afterwards I spent the rest of my time in the city with my fellow RAs and occasionally alone, eating, reading, chatting, and writing. It felt good to be done with the project. There was a lot to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/rome.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Presenting in Rome&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;budapest&#34;&gt;Budapest&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last week of my trip was spent in the lovely Budapest, visiting a friend whom I hadn’t seen in two years. I had visited before, but it was during this second trip that I came to appreciate the city for what it offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrasted with Rome, Budapest feels more open and traditionally European. The city coexists with the natural scenery. Trolley tracks and bike paths line the streets. The friendly but mind-your-own-business Eastern European persona is apparent. It was a much needed escape from the Roman zoo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent some time reading, writing, and hanging out with my beloved friend, but mostly I just looked. At the people. At buildings and at storefronts. At my mind and my own thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An older couple from Israel noticed me doing this, “nothing”, outside a small cafe by the Hungarian National Museum, and we had a long and thoughtful conversation about it. It occurred to me that most people don’t really do this, just looking at things and seeing them as they are. The wife, a teacher at a Waldorf school, thought it was an incredibly important skill to teach her students in a world where our attention is increasingly exploited for profit. I replied that it may not be the most exciting thing to do, &amp;ldquo;nothing&amp;rdquo;, but it provides fertile ground for creativity, serendipity, and reflections to grow, which actually makes it pretty fun. And sometimes a connection you didn’t have before may suddenly and sometimes wildly emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;home&#34;&gt;Home&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t do everything in life, so you have to pick and choose what’s important to you, and unapologetically prune everything else out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists with balanced lives have their priorities in order. It’s perfectly fine to have science define the entirety of one&amp;rsquo;s life, so long as it was a deliberate decision. But this perched image of the scientist can be misleading or harmful to those who want to work as a scientist, but find fulfillment and meaning in other things as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking yesterday down by Champlain Lake, I realized that I had been accompanied by this awful, dreadful feeling of existential angst for nearly every day over the past 3 months. In this state of mind, everything I tried or worked on that wasn’t related to “figuring it out” became a distraction. Something bad. Unproductive. A waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that something needed to change, in both environment and mindset, in both priorities and values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I want to become a scientist anymore, at least in the conventional, academic sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I do want is to be curious. For my brain to feel alert and turned on. For my days to be filled with a sense of wonder, vitality, awe, fascination, and astonishment. I want to “choose a soul that is alert and wide awake,” in the words of the writer Jedidiah Jenkins. This requires dismantling and redefining what work means to me. It requires reexamining the sort of life I want to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward, there are a few leads I’d like to follow. It’s gonna take some work. But life’s too short to compromise for anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/throwing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Throwing rocks&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Bearing Witness</title>
        <link>/posts/2019-06-07-bearing-witness/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2019-06-07-bearing-witness/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There were 16 of us nestled in the sunlit alcove of the church. I looked at the stranger sitting on a navy-blue cushion before me and wondered what she was thinking about. She smiled at me, and I smiled back. We introduced ourselves and made small talk, as did everyone else and their adjacent stranger. Then the bell chimed, and the room fell into silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We turned our gaze to Mike, the PI of the study. He had a gentle voice – like that of a breeze in the wind, calm, cool, wisened – and intense blue eyes that were easy to lose yourself in. Then the instructions came: we were told simply to look into our partner’s eyes for the next few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My partner and I fidgeted and repositioned ourselves on our increasingly stiff and uncomfortable cushions. Our eyes darted toward one another’s, then to the ground and to other objects in the room, then back again to our respective irises. Chocolate brown staring into forest blue. She smiled at me, and I smiled back. It was clear we had never actually looked at anyone like this before. We were two strangers waltzing in a burning room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A minute or two passed before the discomfort was overtaken by a growing sense of awe and openness. The longer I looked at my partner, the more I saw once I had moved beyond the narrow horizon of her eyes. She was no longer just a stranger before me. She had become a multitude of constellating identities and stories, a twisted thread of immutable pasts and yet-to-be-had futures, a long line of unfulfilled promises and unfulfilling heartbreaks, an unimaginable plane of N dimensions, an infinity no mathematician could ever tame or understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Searching for certainties was no longer an option on the vast plains of vulnerability. My eyes no longer wanted to run. They had settled onto hers. There was nowhere left to go or hide. What remained was the raw openness of experience, of bearing witness, of measuring our moments not by the hands of the hour, but by the rapid echoes of our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/clouds.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;meditation&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>The Pale Blue Dot</title>
        <link>/posts/2019-03-15-pale-blue-dot/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2019-03-15-pale-blue-dot/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Propelled into space in 1977, NASA’s scientific objective of launching the Voyager I was to photograph the planets of the outer solar system. They expected the spacecraft to function no further than Saturn. Yet work it did, and it continues to defy expectation up to this day, still traveling at 40,000 miles per hour, somewhere at or beyond the edges of our solar system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Voyager passed Saturn, Carl Sagan – astronomer, cosmologist, astrophysicist, lover and communicator of science – requested that NASA turn the cameras back toward home. He wanted a picture of Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many in the Voyager program were supportive of the idea, but there were concerns about the practical costs of following through with Sagan’s vision. I picture the pragmatists of NASA wondering, “Are we really going to do this? Is this really worth the effort?” Of course, Sagan knew his request would fulfill no scientific objective. But he had more poetic ambitions, for knowledge and progress is limited without a sense of perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can only imagine the poetic candor, timeliness, and confidence Sagan must have exuded while attempting to convince the NASA administration of his wish. On Valentine’s Day of 1990, from 3.7 billion miles away, the Voyager captured this photo of Earth, immortalized by Sagan as the “Pale Blue Dot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thinking of this picture now in light of the current cultural, political, and global tensions we are all facing. I am thinking of Sagan’s arresting reflection that should reorient even the most cynical of us. I quote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this distant vantage point, the Earth might not seem of any particular interest. But for us, it’s different. Consider again that dot. That’s here. That’s home. That’s us. On it everyone you love, everyone you know, everyone you ever heard of, every human being who ever was, lived out their lives. The aggregate of our joy and suffering, thousands of confident religions, ideologies, and economic doctrines, every hunter and forager, every hero and coward, every creator and destroyer of civilization, every king and peasant, every young couple in love, every mother and father, hopeful child, inventor and explorer, every teacher of morals, every corrupt politician, every ‘superstar,’ every ‘supreme leader,’ every saint and sinner in the history of our species lived there — on a mote of dust suspended in a sunbeam.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; The Earth is a very small stage in a vast cosmic arena. Think of the rivers of blood spilled by all those generals and emperors so that in glory and triumph they could become the momentary masters of a fraction of a dot. Think of the endless cruelties visited by the inhabitants of one corner of this pixel on the scarcely distinguishable inhabitants of some other corner. How frequent their misunderstandings, how eager they are to kill one another, how fervent their hatreds. Our posturings, our imagined self-importance, the delusion that we have some privileged position in the universe, are challenged by this point of pale light. Our planet is a lonely speck in the great enveloping cosmic dark. In our obscurity — in all this vastness — there is no hint that help will come from elsewhere to save us from ourselves. The Earth is the only world known, so far, to harbor life. There is nowhere else, at least in the near future, to which our species could migrate. Visit, yes. Settle, not yet. Like it or not, for the moment, the Earth is where we make our stand. It has been said that astronomy is a humbling and character-building experience. There is perhaps no better demonstration of the folly of human conceits than this distant image of our tiny world. To me, it underscores our responsibility to deal more kindly with one another and to preserve and cherish the pale blue dot, the only home we’ve ever known.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s here. That’s home. All of it. A tiny pale blue dot. A mote of dust suspended in a sunbeam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/Pale_Blue_Dot.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://visibleearth.nasa.gov/view.php?id=52392&#34;&gt;By Voyager 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Shoreless Seeds and Stardust</title>
        <link>/posts/2019-03-12-shoreless-seeds-and-stardust/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2019-03-12-shoreless-seeds-and-stardust/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I ventured out onto the lake today, this time beyond the frozen crest that marks the boundary between bay and lake, contemplating the last line of Maria Popova’s Figuring: “What will survive of us are shoreless seeds and stardust.” My saunter figured into a sprint as the mountains came into view, and soon the voices behind me were no more than whispers. Minutes later I ran into a couple playing in the snow. We were the only three out on the edge of the lake’s center, three constellating islands happy just to be. I smiled at them and carried on ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ski tracks and foot trails slowly gave way to the unsentimental forces of snow and wind, erasing, leaving behind no trace of human curiosity, ingenuity, legacy, as I moved further from civilization. I reached the center and looked back toward shore, then to the skies above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that, by some collision of chance and choice, we exist in this cosmic blink of a moment, so short yet so sweet, should give us pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standing on that expanse, alone though filled with images of another, alone yet accompanied by the unique neuronal flutterings that have mapped onto my brain the contours of a newly discovered body and mind, I thought of how easy it would have been to ascribe my good fortune - our good fortune - to the hands of an all powerful force. This beautiful impulse toward certitude is certainly a defining feature of our species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I took a breath and remembered there exists a narrative more compelling than the man-made stories predicated on fear of the afterlife. One only has to look up at the stars. “What will survive of us are shoreless seeds and stardust.” One day we will close our eyes for the last time, and return to that space from which we all came, forever constellating and transmuting, forming and reforming, dancing and figuring on the thread of eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I turned back toward Burlington and began to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/frozenlake.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Lessons in Adulthood</title>
        <link>/posts/adulthood/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/adulthood/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;crossroads&#34;&gt;Crossroads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My year of service with City Year, New Hampshire was coming to an end. I knew that I didn’t want to become a teacher anymore, but I still liked the idea of shaping the young minds of the future, so I applied to Boston University’s Masters program in Educational Leadership and Policy Studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was waiting for my flight home in O’Hare International Airport when I received the news. The man sitting next to me happened to notice – he must have glimpsed the email’s subject line – and congratulated me. I called my parents and told my friends. I had been accepted, and everyone was happy for me – everyone but me. Then the simple thought occurred: I didn’t actually care about educational leadership or policy studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adulthood is full of moments like this. Hard decisions, crossroads, uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Letting go and starting anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;building&#34;&gt;Building&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In grade school and college, your friends and peers are more or less handed to you. The goals are predefined and clearly laid out, and the path to success is linear: show up to class, do your homework, study hard, and pass the exams. And at your side throughout these years are the world’s best cheerleaders: your parents. In failure and success, in love and in heartbreak, they are gracious, generous, and ever so timely in their steadfast presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you graduate though, it’s not so obvious what you’re supposed to be doing. It’s likely that you’ve moved away from your parents, your friends, and the place you once called home, all in pursuit of a life to claim as your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How, then, do we begin navigating these uncharted waters? We start equipped only with our preexisting beliefs and premature identities. Yet problems arise when the demands of our changing circumstances steer us toward new ways of being, when the architecture that once held up our lives begins to crumble under the weight of newfound uncertainties. These are the moments in which we must summon the courage and willingness to change, to grow above and beyond our own limits and capacities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trials&#34;&gt;Trials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up is largely a game of trial and error, and no more is this clearer than in the context dating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to know what you are looking for in a partner without any prior experience. You may have some basic idea of what you desire based on past conversations with family and friends, what you’ve seen and hear in the media, and what you’ve experienced. But until these ideas are tested, it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to discern what your own beliefs are from that of others. Up until this point, your beliefs aren’t truly yours at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months ago, I was complaining to one of my coworkers about how hard it was to make friends and to meet people outside of school. She suggested I create an online dating profile on Tinder and Bumble. I thought this was a terrible idea, partly because of the superficiality of these platforms, but also because I harbored the belief that no one would want to date me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The qualities I prided myself on – patience, thoughtfulness, curiosity – weren’t as easily displayed in five hundred or less characters, much less in five pictures. And when it came to the looks department, I felt like no more than an average fish swimming in the competitive waters of online dating. Still, I went ahead and created a profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve since learned that people do swipe right largely based on how attractive you are – no surprises there. But more fortunately perhaps, the second reason for my initial hesitations stands corrected: I did match with people – a lot more, in fact, than I thought I would – and I like to believe that it was for more than surface appearances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first date I went on was with a cardiac nurse from North Carolina. Our text conversations were filled with lengthy essays about the role of mindfulness in our lives, the challenges of preparing for and running a Spartan race, the places we’ve traveled, and other non-superficial topics. They were varied and thoughtful – ”the most wholesome I’ve ever had on Tinder,” she said. I was hooked. Maybe Tinder wasn’t so superficial after all, I thought. Perhaps beneath the surface, its users were bound together by a deep-seated desire to find lasting and meaningful relationships, not just hook-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met a few days later down at the waterfront. It was the perfect Autumn afternoon. Her profile pictures had failed to capture just how attractive she was in person. We took a long stroll around the park, and my initial nervousness quickly gave way to the flow of our conversation. It was a great first date in my book. Discovery of shared interests, lots of laughter and intellectual banter, and she was interested in seeing me again. Later that week, I invited her to go rock climbing. And to this day, she still hasn’t responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the next few days immersed in a suffocating haze of confusion: what went wrong? Why hasn’t she responded yet? Didn’t she say that she want to see me again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hadn’t occurred to me yet that “ghosting” was a common phenomenon in the age of digital dating, the worst kind of cliffhanger. I soon realized that this was to be expected, a part of the game. And the only way to win was to keep playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of my dates improved as I continued to meet with more people. I was ghosted again by the second person I went on a date with, but she reached out and apologized a week later, saying that she wanted to see where things would go with someone else. That stung a bit, but it was better than being left in total radio silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I met Carmen. I spent more time with her than I had with anyone else, which was already a success in my mind. But our dates felt more like friendly hangouts, and we soon realized the romantic spark wasn’t there. Oddly enough, I felt ok with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I was fine with how things turned out between Carmen and I may seem trivial, but it wasn’t. I had gone through enough ghosting, terrible dates, and prolonged periods of emotional confusion to learn that it’s never worth the effort to pursue someone who you feel lukewarm about. And if the romantic potential is there, then it didn’t need to be rushed. “Things take the time they take,” wrote the poet Mary Oliver, in the formation of relationships, in becoming an adult, in the construction of a life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everything was a lost cause between Carmen and I. She introduced me to the alluring world of latin dancing, she showed me how to be more romantically confident with women (poke the touch barrier!), and she became my friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dating is much less about finding the perfect partner than it is about developing a better sense of self-awareness, and accepting what you find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hypotheses&#34;&gt;Hypotheses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the time I started online dating, I began working on a research project under the guidance of my boss, Alexi. We were interested in how puberty affected a child&amp;rsquo;s neurocognition. Did their current stage of pubertal development hold any sway over how well they performed on various neurocognitive tasks? My hunch was that it did, but hunches are no more than the static platforms from which knowledge is discovered and reconfigured. They are only the starting points of inquiry. Hunches must be scrutinized under the microscope of science if they are to illuminate the contours of the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What leads all scientific endeavors is the notorious hypothesis. Hypotheses are simple things really: they’re testable guesses, grounded assumptions based on past research and existing knowledge, questions we want answers to refined in the form of a falsifiable statement. We don’t ever truly know where our hypotheses will take us or what sort of answers – or lack thereof – will emerge from them, but that’s precisely why they’re worth exploring. They take us one step closer to reality, should we be bold enough to follow their lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had moved to Vermont to explore a more personal question: did I want to pursue a PhD in Clinical Psychology? Bits and pieces of the answer revealed themselves as I worked on my research project. I enjoyed analyzing, visualizing, and playing with the data, but when it came time to review the scientific literature, I quickly realized that I disdained the writing of academic research papers, perhaps the quintessential task that defines scientific careers. They are restricted and confining, catered to inform but not to persuade or inspire, as maybe they should be in the realm of science. Yet it was this fact alone that made me reconsider the PhD route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were other things too: the constant need to write and fight for grants; stories of talented graduates struggling to find employment and enjoyment outside of work; and the time commitment it all took. It just doesn’t seem like the life I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;awareness&#34;&gt;Awareness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As kids, we internalize a specific set of ideas and beliefs about the world based on the views and actions of our parents, the education we received, and the environments we were a part of. Some remain true in the face of change and challenge, some should be discarded all together, while others may require further refinement. This process of continual self-molding, of reevaluating and adapting the hypotheses we live by, is what constitutes the art of growing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It begins by developing a keener sense of self-awareness, and how we do that is by embracing the mindset of a scientist. Experiment. Try new things. Put yourself in novel situations and note how you react. Go one step further and record your explorations in a journal. Ask yourself why you reacted the way you did and write it down. Is that how you truly felt? Or are you conforming to outdated but deeply rooted narratives? Do you need to refine or change the hypotheses you operate by?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auditing yourself is a difficult process, and what you find isn’t always pretty. You may discover the incessant need to please others because it was the only way you got attention as a child. You may feel that your emotions aren’t worth expressing because being vulnerable has always lead to pain. You may believe that you’re too unattractive, too boring, too stupid – too much of anything! – to ever be loved by someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet once these patterns are exposed and out in the open, they begin to lose their domineering grip. They no longer need to be true. By seeing them for what they are, by acknowledging the nature of their false fatalism, we are freed from their stranglehold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is from the vantage of awareness that we possess the opportunity to define what it means to be an adult, and how we want to live our lives. Of course, what we choose to answer with isn’t forever set in stone. It is subject to the whims of time, circumstance, and reinterpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the beautiful paradox. Becoming an adult isn’t about becoming anything or anyone at all. It’s about recognizing that you are the becoming, a shifting constellation, an everchanging tide, the unnameable, label-defying confluence of chance and choice. It’s about being aware that the landscape of possibility is open to you, and making the leap when the moment beckons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/wing.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Mary Oliver</title>
        <link>/posts/2019-01-19-mary-oliver/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2019-01-19-mary-oliver/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We first met in the biting winter nights of my service year in New Hampshire. I listened with full attention as she illuminated the nuances and contours of the world through the written word, hers, words that continue to remind me I am never truly alone, words that continue to show me the world is always at offer to the playground of my imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, when faced with the task of figuring what direction my life should go, she visited me in Spain and reminded me not to worry, that things will take the time they take, that even Saint Augustine followed many roads before he became Saint Augustine. It is all a journey, she said, a long, wide, and deep dive into infinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also told me there are certain moments in life that cry out to be fulfilled, like telling someone you love them. I followed her word when that moment came for me. The woman, someone who cherished August blackberries, someone I loved dearly, gave me a box full of darkness in return. I later learned that this, too, was a gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She came again when, during a morning walk down by the lake, I heard the call of wild geese, harsh and exciting, high in the clean blue air. I had been preoccupied with finding a sense of place, a sense that I belonged in the family of things, of knowing what to do next. I turned my gaze toward the geese, and my problems hushed their determined utterances. I watched the geese fly across the open sky, losing all sense of time, and when they flew beyond the range of my vision, I was inhabited by a lighter sense of being. I had taken flight with the geese, or rather, they had taken me. They reminded that I was an animal among animals, a lucky collection of stardust, something alive and wonderfully capable of experiencing the shared wonders of existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I and many others will continue to feel the echoes of her singular devotion to her one wild and precious life. Even darkness can be a gift, a fire that awakens the sleeping soul, a light that guides us to our higher selves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To Mary Oliver, for teaching me that the sacred is always within reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/maryoliver.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/mary-oliver-helped-us-stay-amazed&#34;&gt;Photo Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Letters to a Young Scientist</title>
        <link>/posts/2018-08-05-letters-to-a-young-scientist/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2018-08-05-letters-to-a-young-scientist/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Veteran biologist and teacher of science Edward Wilson lays out a few principles for the young scientist to keep in mind as he/she/they proceed in their career:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put passion ahead of training. Feel out in any way you can what you most want to do in science, or technology, or some other science-related profession. Obey that passion as long as it lasts. Feed it with the knowledge the mind needs to grow. Sample other subjects, acquire a general education in science, and be smart enough to switch to a greater love if one appears. But don’t just drift through courses in science hoping that love will come to you. Maybe it will, but don’t take the chance. As in other big choices in your life, there is too much at stake. Decision and hard work based on enduring passion will never fail you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this I add: commit yourself to curiosity, and follow it wherever it may lead you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding math in the sciences, and the dread often associated with learning and applying it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every scientist, whether researcher, technologist, or teacher, of whatever competence in mathematics, there exists a discipline in science for which that level of mathematical competence is enough to achieve excellence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science rewards endeavors into the rare and the niche, the unexplored and neglected. Wilson writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March away from the sound of the guns. Observe the fray from a distance, and while you are at it, consider making your own fray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good way to frame problems in science, and in life:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the search for scientific discoveries, every problem is an opportunity. The more difficult the problem, the greater the likely importance of its solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideal scientist thinks like a poet and only later works like a bookkeeper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/wilson.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://museum.unl.edu/research/entomology/workers/EWilson.htm&#34;&gt;Photo Attribution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Serendipity</title>
        <link>/posts/2018-01-17-serendipity/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2018-01-17-serendipity/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We sift through life without any compasses to guide us through the messy unknown, like aimless treasure hunters searching for diamonds in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unknown scares us. We&amp;rsquo;re not so comfortable immersed in this infinite expanse. Maybe this is why the human brain has evolved the ability to construe stories from unrelated anecdotes and scattered tidbits: we find comfort in connecting the dots, we tell ourselves everything happens for a reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stories provide our lives a sense of coherence, a hedge to prop ourselves on in the face of uncertainty. Sometimes they make things more beautiful, sometimes they prompt us to act; often times, they leave us wondering. &amp;ldquo;She likes me––right?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life will always present us with opportunities that have the potential to profoundly alter our course along its river. It may be a person we meet, a change of job or city, a sobering rejection, a desire for more out of life. A cup of tea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These events are no more than events in themselves. But perhaps more beautifully, if we allow them to be, they are the unexpected serendipities that shape who we are, and who we become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is an edgeless marble; serendipity gives it form. What was once meaningless becomes something of impossible importance. The stagnant becomes animate. It looks natural and feels seamless. It sings and breathes and dances and has a reason for existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serendipity gives us permission to own a small part of life. It lets us grasp and claim this unusual sense of being, this constellating moment of existence, this thing we call &lt;em&gt;My&lt;/em&gt; life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello Vermont.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/scoutandco.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Winter</title>
        <link>/posts/winter/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/winter/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Arbiter of cessation, master of endings, &lt;br&gt;
a gust inevitably endured. &lt;br&gt;
Clench your jaw now, the exchange is complete: &lt;br&gt;
Snow and frost for people and sidewalks. &lt;br&gt;
Inches and burdens &lt;br&gt;
for sauntered footfalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a season between seasons &lt;br&gt;
a bridge that is crossed by the plentiful few. &lt;br&gt;
Adults and scientists seek it endlessly &lt;br&gt;
though only the children know &lt;br&gt;
of its whereabouts. &lt;br&gt;
But don’t bother with asking–– &lt;br&gt;
they’re sworn to the promises of secrecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I make no guarantees of my own: &lt;br&gt;
Certainty is certainly &lt;br&gt;
out of the picture. &lt;br&gt;
Though some day you may catch hint of &lt;br&gt;
what it is and &lt;br&gt;
where it may be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clue: &lt;br&gt;
It&amp;rsquo;s right in front of you. &lt;br&gt;
Between one breath of Winter and &lt;br&gt;
One sigh of Spring &lt;br&gt;
There exists everything &lt;br&gt;
essential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/winter.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Forgiveness</title>
        <link>/posts/2018-01-09-forgiveness/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2018-01-09-forgiveness/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness moves us toward a better future by inviting us to look at the past, at the unrelenting, painful ghosts that continue to permeate and darken every corner of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we need to feel rage, to tussle with guilt, to fall into our sorrows before we can forgive. No, forgiveness is not about avoiding these emotions. Rather, forgiveness asks us to show up daily with unwavering courage, compassion, receptivity, and kindness. It asks us if we are ready to build the bridge on which we must cross in order to move beyond our past selves. Forgiveness is answering the call for a spiritual freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness is a process. We know intellectually why we should forgive, but truth must be felt within our bones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness is not easy. It takes work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness does not always mean to let the other person back into our lives. We may still declare, “I do not want you here. I do not want you in my life.” It is the release of our psychic terrors; it is letting go of the anger, rage, and suffering we have brought onto ourselves under the guise of their name. Forgiveness moves past victimhood and emboldens action. Forgiveness is for the forgiver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness asks us to let go of the pain we’ve held onto so long. It asks us to realize our own power. It asks us to make room for love. It asks us to embrace what is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgiveness asks us if we are ready to love again. It asks us if we are willing to risk getting hurt again in order to participate in the wonderful game of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/forgive.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Feelings</title>
        <link>/posts/2018-01-06-feelings/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2018-01-06-feelings/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Feelings are fleeting by nature, like the passage of clouds on a warm summer day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though too often we wear them like immutable masks and declare, &amp;ldquo;This is me. This is all I will ever be.&amp;rdquo; Sad. Resentful. Despondent. Happy. In truth they are masks, transient facades that hide a more true and vulnerable sense of self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We put these masks on when we&amp;rsquo;re scared, when we&amp;rsquo;re too afraid to ask for attention and love; when we&amp;rsquo;re on the verge of breaking, but don&amp;rsquo;t know how to ask for help. When we&amp;rsquo;re searching for something solid in the face of groundlessness. Even happiness is something we try too hard to hold onto, strangling it of all significance in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feelings are signals: they point toward ourselves, toward the unknown. But they are not us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take this non-attached perspective is more terrifying than the feelings themselves; we would rather feel angry and sad than to risk being a drop in the ocean (Yet, what is an ocean but a multitude of drops?). Non-attachment is not detachment. Detaching is active avoidance whereas non-attachment is active engagement––detachment runs while non-attachment sits and feels and notices with non-judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the vantage of non-attachment, we can see our feelings as they truly are: simply feelings, waves that come and go like the seasons; things as permanent as the illusory grounds they stand upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then who are we if not our feelings? What is under the mask? What is left?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are something else, something both more and less grounded, a shifting paradox, something wildly, unconditionally beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are the calm after a storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A newborn&amp;rsquo;s first breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiny motes of existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beam piercing through the darkness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The light of Being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proof of grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/feelings.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brainpickings.org/2015/02/26/the-well-of-being-jean-pierre-weill/&#34;&gt;Image Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>Love Letter</title>
        <link>/posts/2018-01-02-love-letter/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/2018-01-02-love-letter/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear stranger, &lt;br&gt;
I know we’ve just met but, &lt;br&gt;
I love you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love you more than you could know. &lt;br&gt;
I love you unconditionally. &lt;br&gt;
I love you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot know your pain, your experience, &lt;br&gt;
Your suffering. That is all yours. &lt;br&gt;
But you do not have to bear it &lt;br&gt;
alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dance with melancholy &lt;br&gt;
And sing out your blues but please &lt;br&gt;
Don&amp;rsquo;t stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk to me. Tell me about it. &lt;br&gt;
Whatever you feel, feel it. &lt;br&gt;
Then do one thing for yourself–– &lt;br&gt;
One act of self-love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won&amp;rsquo;t always feel good &lt;br&gt;
Like going to the gym &lt;br&gt;
Or eating your vegetables &lt;br&gt;
Or calling your mother &lt;br&gt;
Or crying–– &lt;br&gt;
Crying helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But know this:&lt;br&gt;
Admitting weakness is not weak.&lt;br&gt;
It is simply the beginning
of something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So tear up and throw out &lt;br&gt;
Those old pictures of your lover &lt;br&gt;
Into your favorite trash bin. &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forgive them and forgive yourself. &lt;br&gt;
And when you’re done you can begin &lt;br&gt;
Loving again. &lt;br&gt;
Loving yourself. &lt;br&gt;
Loving life. &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may feel &lt;br&gt;
just an ounce more ready &lt;br&gt;
to engage in a world &lt;br&gt;
filled with facts and problems,
awe and inspiration,
rosebuds and thorns,
heartbreak and love. &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may feel &lt;br&gt;
just an ounce more ready &lt;br&gt;
to let ourselves &lt;br&gt;
be hurt again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/wispflower.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;flowers&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>18: Home</title>
        <link>/posts/home/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/home/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After Belgium, I spent one night in Prague and took a bus to Hungary the next morning. I stayed in Budapest for 10 days with Eszter, the Hungarian woman I had a crush on at the beginning of this whole adventure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt strange, to be back in the swing of normalcy, as if such a thing was possible after such a journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no bitterness or resentment toward Marieke. Actually, I was alarmed at how fast it seemed I was “moving on”. It was as if my mind had compartmentalized the Camino experience, like it was all some dream I had just awoken from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I ws with Eszter, it felt like nothing had changed. We talked with the same depth and intensity we had in Canada, and I seemed to be living and acting like a normal human being. The feelings I had for her were still there too, which surprised me. Was I already losing the Camino?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that it was over didn&amp;rsquo;t hit me until I was home in California on October 26th, 2017. A teary-eyed Mother was waiting for me in LAX. She said I looked like a tan monk. We went home. I hugged my Dad and my brother. I shared brief stories of my experience, then went to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few days, I fell into a state of deep loneliness, despondence, and longing. My friends and parents tried to soothe my grievances, but they couldn&amp;rsquo;t. How could they? I was falling into a hole that simply didn&amp;rsquo;t exist in their world. &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re home now. Shouldn&amp;rsquo;t you be happy?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days later, it became clear to me that I missed life on the road. But why? What was it that I missed? The simplicity? The friendships? The solitude? The clarity? A sense of purpose? Purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was doing it all wrong. I was trying too hard to return to a place in my mind that was concrete and grounded; trying too hard to refit my life into the straitjacket I had fought so hard to escape from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose: I had searched the Camino for such a thing, but never found it. Only when I had abandoned my search and surrendered the idea that I could control each and every ounce of my life, did I finally understand what was worth living for: growth, and love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense, these things are also a form of purpose, and perhaps that is the great paradox: we continually strive for meaning when nothing really matters in the grand scheme of things. Perhaps that is what keeps us going – we get to decide what matters and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose is what keeps us afloat in our day to day, year to year existence until the moment we take our final breath. But life only matters, to paraphrase David Foster Wallace, before that final breath. It is here that we have our greatest opportunity: we get to choose what is and isn&amp;rsquo;t meaningful to us, what&amp;rsquo;s worth and not worth fighting for. Although the grand stage is, in some ways, already set, we get to decide within the parameters of these rules how we want to play the game. And the wonderful thing is, these rules are flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose then I wasn&amp;rsquo;t ready to decide yet, what was and wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth dedicating my time and attention to, and I had to be fine with that. I had to be fine with sitting alone in the unknown, as terrifying as it is at times. What helped was realizing that it is more terrifying to latch onto a purpose not designed and chosen by you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world around me had not changed. It was I who felt displaced, dislodged, different. I recognized it in the way I perceived things, in the way I talked with my friends, in the way I thought about time. I could feel it in the growing distance between who I thought I was, and who I was becoming. Only once I had accepted that I had fundamentally changed, that I had grown, did I begin to find a sense of Home again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home isn&amp;rsquo;t really about a place or its inhabitants. Home begins and grows from the inner wellspring of one&amp;rsquo;s being. In a sense then, home truly is where the heart is. Home is a landscape we carve from the varieties of experience that so happen to grace us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am reminded of a quote by Joanna Field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I did not know that I could only get the most out of life by giving myself up to it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That feeling I had in Santiago –– of wholeness, interconnectedness, fluidity, shapelessness, of being something outside of myself –– it didn&amp;rsquo;t last long, but something in me had shifted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world feels more beautiful. Perspective is easier to hold and maintain. The everyday is less mundane and more majestic. Little things don&amp;rsquo;t bother me as much. Peace and contentment are more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I will still have my bad days and mood swings. I will still have my moments of doubt and paralysis when the grip of the darker depths of my mind take hold, moments when I am unable to see the light gleaming over the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I know now it is always possible to get out, to surrender, to let go and be still, to feel what I feel without attachment, to be impermanent, to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This moment. This beautiful, precious, seamless moment. This is it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/home.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>17: The Final Goodbye</title>
        <link>/posts/final-goodbye/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/final-goodbye/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;p&gt;I arrive in Belgium late in the afternoon. The weather is exceptional: half-clouded skies with no reservation of sunlight, a perfect balance of cool and warm. I exit from the train station and hoist myself against a tall statue, eagerly looking for my squirrelly Belgium. 15 minutes pass before I spot her standing only 20 meters behind me, clad in a gray hoodie and a black leather jacket, lightly faded jeans and the tall leather boots of an amazon. Upon realizing that it was me looking at her, we sprint toward one another and embrace as if someone had just come home from war. It felt good to be in her arms again. Her radiating eyes still contained the ability to fully arrest my sensibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We catch up over coffee at a nearby restaurant. She reflects on the difficulties of returning home, the growing tension between her and her parents, and the continued struggle of trying to find balance within her medical studies. I tell her about the rest of my time on the Camino – the magical moments, the people I met, reaching Santiago, the decision not to go further, saying goodbye. It feels surreal, the fact that I was in Belgium, staying with someone I had met on the Camino only weeks prior, the fact that I was there with Marieke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still confused about my feelings toward her. I believed I was in love, but something about it just didn’t feel right. Was it because we had met on the Camino? Would it have been too good to be true? Or did I simply get the impression that she wouldn’t love me back in the way I loved her? Was it really love? Or something else entirely?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was walking on a thin wire, unsure of when I would fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later we go to a park and continue our conversation. She mentions that Stepan had sent her a firey, passionate email admitting that he had fallen in love with her the moment they met. She seemed confused and a bit bewildered by the letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often wondered why he decided to walk the Camino, a question he always deflected or never gave a straight answer for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We brainstorm about what his motivations were for walking the Camino. Maybe he was a lost-soul searching for love; maybe he was just a normal guy struggling in life like everyone else, seeking solace in a foreign land. Maybe he did something unforgivable back in his home country. Whatever the case, the Camino had a way of connecting people despite the mysteries, sometimes because of them. On the Camino, the past wasn&amp;rsquo;t as important as the fact that we were simply there, walking together, sharing our common humanity, sharing a love of the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, our conversation transpires toward the topic of us – me and her – and she mentions something I will never forget: “You know, back on the Camino, I could have fallen in love with you. I wanted to. We grew so close so quickly, and it scared me a little. But I couldn&amp;rsquo;t. It would have changed the reasons for why we were there.” It was strange to talk so openly about us like this, but I reply that I understand and felt the same way. Though a different dialogue was playing in my head: Yes, love does change people, but that’s precisely what makes it so beautiful. Wasn’t the Camino about embracing all that comes your way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re in her room, listening to Leonard Cohen. The question still lingers: do I love her? Does she love me? I won’t know until we talk about it. I won’t know until it&amp;rsquo;s out in the open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m afraid. What if I jeopardize what we already have? No, we’re different. We can talk about anything and everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My gut feels like a block of lead is hanging from it. My heart is beating faster and faster. It wants to hide. To run. To fly away. To breathe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still I don&amp;rsquo;t know what to make of it, how to admit how I felt. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even sure of what I was feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brittle piece of glass is standing on its corner at the edge of a table. Any amount of tumult or movement will tip it over. In the distance, a storm with the power to break trees, and men, is coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fire begins to kindle, and I turn toward Marieke. She looks straight at me. Through me. Inaudible words enter the air. Time collapses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I think I&amp;rsquo;m in love with you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emptiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A messy knot of shoestrings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A moment between moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Phil, I have never met anyone like you before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we have, I have never had it with anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are so special to me&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could fall in love with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your love has no bounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your love is so pure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You––”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something falls. A tiny piece of glass has shattered into a thousand tiny fractals. Time begins to sweep them into the pan of reality. A naked thread remainsmm and the voice of Leonard Cohen echoes in the nearby distance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your letters they all say that you&amp;rsquo;re beside me now.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Then why do I feel alone?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m standing on a ledge and your fine spider web&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;is fastening my ankle to a stone.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now so long, Marianne, it&amp;rsquo;s time that we began&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;To laugh and cry and cry and laugh about it all again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, Marieke and I go to an African church service. I feel numb but put on a front. We sing with the choir and listen to a genial priest preach about love, forgiveness, redemption. I hear nothing. &lt;em&gt;What the hell do you know about love?&lt;/em&gt; We eat, drink, chat, and walk around. Things go on as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we’re in the train station. A young, affectionate couple is sitting near us. They&amp;rsquo;re utterly in love, grossly enmeshed and atop one another. Time halts once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anger. Sadness. Disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No. I can&amp;rsquo;t be angry, sad, disappointed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To be in love, to have fallen in love, to have been heartbroken. That, in a way, is a gift.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I rationalizing my pain? I don’t know. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We embrace one last time and say our goodbyes. I board the train and take one last look at her through the opaque window. She looks back. I wave and turn inwards. A tear begins to creep down my cheek. I close my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I guess this is it then.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engine whirs to life, and slowly, slowly, I am taken by the arms of an unknown future. The distance between dream and reality begins to grow, and I am pulled against my will toward the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere else in the world, the sun is shining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-final-letter-october-15th-2017&#34;&gt;My Final Letter: October 15th, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say that, as I sit here in the airport, I am feeling heartbroken. It&amp;rsquo;s not your fault; it&amp;rsquo;s no ones. It&amp;rsquo;s simply the nature of love. Initially, I felt numb because I was denying the fact that I was in love. It was one of the purest truths I have ever fought, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to get hurt; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to jeopardize our friendship; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to accept that maybe it just wasn&amp;rsquo;t right. And maybe all of my fears and insecurities are false, and the reason for why I feel what I do now is completely different. I may never know why, but it really doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter – it wasn&amp;rsquo;t meant to be. So I have to accept it – I will accept it. And in the process, I am letting the soft animal of my body feel what it feels, and love what it loves (Mary Oliver is on my mind as I write this to you).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I will get back up stronger, more able to give love, more able to receive it, every day from this point on. I don&amp;rsquo;t think we ever know when we are ready for love, but that should not stop us from trying. Because that is what the truest form of love is. That is the only way we know it&amp;rsquo;s real. By trying. By loving. By getting hurt, and, if you’re one of the lucky ones, doing it all over again – maybe with a little less hurt each time. Maybe.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M, know that you are so special, so able to receive, and give love. Don&amp;rsquo;t ever let anyone else tell you otherwise, including, especially, You.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember the day when you told me that you had never felt love before. That was on day 4 of our Camino. I then made a promise to myself to show you how it feels. I don’t know if I have been successful. But what I believe is, what we had, that was love. It’s possible. It’s real. Hang onto it. Carry it with you. Give it to someone else who will love you back.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don&amp;rsquo;t blame yourself for the way I currently feel – I’ll be fine. I tell you this because you have been my best friend, you have taught me so much about life. Truly, I cannot fathom the depth of our relationship, and I cannot begin to express how thankful I am. I am tearing up as I write this, out of such joy and gratitude. This letter, I suppose, will mark the end of my Camino. It has taught me the final lesson I needed to learn: what it means to love. &lt;br&gt;
-P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/final.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>16: Santiago</title>
        <link>/posts/santiago/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/santiago/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“How we spend our days is, of course, how we spend our lives.”
–Annie Dillard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-8-2017-day-31&#34;&gt;October 8, 2017 - Day 31&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pedrouzo, Spain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 20 kilometers, I will reach Santiago de Compostela. The anticipation has left me sleepless. Ali and Karen are fast asleep. Hope to see them again soon. I pack my things and make a quiet exit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s dark out. Cars lie dormant under the hazy hue of flickering streetlights. Shop-signs strobe with a familiar fluorescence. I’m on the corner of a three-way intersection, eating a bun Karen had given me the night before. A wiry cat pokes its nose around, perhaps searching for food. Not too far ahead, I hear the rhythmic clacking of steel against pavement and rock. I finish my bun and proceed into the twilight, guided by nothing more than a small yellow arrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurons fire, muscles tense. One leg initiates, the other balances. Knee propels forward, heel touches ground. A weight shifts from posterior end to anterior front. Heel lifts, toes tip, a leg swings. One step, repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have suffered. I have endured pain. I have grown. I am no longer under the illusion that life is best lived in pasts, shoulds, and futures. This is it. The people. The weather. The circumstances. Dusted boots and tall rucksacks. A sunflower. Cobalt skies. Birdsong. Valleys. One leg in front of the other. Trotting. Walking. Sauntering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strange thing happened. 10 kilometers from Santiago, while walking along a sidewalk, I was either hallucinating or vividly imagining the presence of every person I had met on the Camino. Matilde and Franca were tiptoeing across the fence to my left, as if on a tightrope. Closer to me was Stepan, Jim, and Kathy. Marieke was to my right. Everyone else was behind me, walking in silence. I realize that I have walked in solitude, but never have I been alone. The people, they have found a permanent place within my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purpose may give direction to the journey, but it is our immediate presence and attention that gives it meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago awaits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Santiago&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reach Santiago de Compostela on October 8th of 2017. It&amp;rsquo;s a Sunday. I&amp;rsquo;m in a dreamy state of mind, not at all aware of time and unsure of what to expect upon reaching the cathedral. I sift through crowds of tourists and pilgrims, between narrow streets and alleyways, guided by nothing more than a yellow arrow. The sound of bagpipes and commotion fill the air. Something smells delicious. Anticipation is coursing through my veins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/santiago2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walk to the center of the plaza, dismount my rucksack, and sit for awhile. I look at the faces surrounding me, searching for a sign. I feel nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I turn my attention and notice a man looking at me. We stare at each other for what seemed like an eternity. The look in his eyes spoke to me: Yes, you are here. Yes, you have made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I begin to cry. Peace and stillness, awe and gratitude, love and surrender; I am filled with the energy of raw, unfiltered emotion. The boundary between the world and I dissipates. I feel connected, whole, complete. I was no longer just Phil. I was a fluid, living, impermeable being that simply lived behind a mask called Phil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people around me suddenly become more than just people. They&amp;rsquo;re human beings with families, friends, and feelings of their own; they are each in possession of their own unique stories, lives they’ve lived and will continue to live. Their eyes emit a beautiful, radiating light, a light I can only describe as the light of Being, a light that says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I am human. I too feel love, pain, suffering, joy, curiosity, wonder. I am you. You are me. A perfect bundle of imperfections. And here we are, together, on a journey across Spain, across life, living a shared existence on a tiny blue mote called Earth amid a less tiny, wildly unknown universe. This is it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The man approaches me in tears, and we hold each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/santiago3.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-9-2017-the-day-after&#34;&gt;October 9, 2017 - The Day After&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago de Compostela is the official endpoint of the Camino, though some pilgrims decide to walk the extra 90 or so kilometers to Finisterre, a coastal city at the edge of Spain, the end of the world. I had intended to end my journey there, but something convinced me otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked for 20 kilometers before feeling that something was off. It just didn’t feel the same. My sense of purpose was gone. Why had I decided to continue in the first place? I have always known how to persevere, how to press on, how to move forward – it had carried me through the pain, to Santiago. But something was telling me the journey needed to end in Santiago. So I walked to the next town and took a bus back to Santiago. In the past, I would have felt a pang of regret, a bruising of the ego, for not muscling through to the end. But I did not feel any regret or a longing for more. I was content. I had had enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was one of the best decisions I made on the Camino. Over the next 4 days, I was able to say goodbye to all of the significant people I had met:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/santiago4.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ali and Karen (the brother and sister I met on my second to last day). They “adopted” me, and I really bonded with Ali. He felt like a long-lost older brother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/santiago5.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jim and Kathy (nearly cried after seeing them. It had been at least 1.5 weeks since we had last seen each other. They were my first friends. Kathy said, “The journey is coming full-circle.&amp;rdquo; Indeed, it was.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/santiago6.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, me and my favorite Germans: Franca and Matilde. I ran into them right after running into Jim and Kathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/santiago7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karaoke!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/santiago8.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey would not have been the same without them and the many others with whom I do not have pictures with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there was still one story left to close: Marieke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still had to go see about a girl.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>15: Letters Worth Czeching Out</title>
        <link>/posts/letters-czech/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/letters-czech/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;p&gt;I wrote these letters to my friend, Stepan, from the Czech Republic. Including them because they might help to create a better picture of my experience. He had joined M and I a few days before M left. These letters were written afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-23-2017&#34;&gt;September 23, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey it&amp;rsquo;s Phil.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked to Hontanas yesterday from Burgos (about 30 km). It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful village worth staying at. Today I&amp;rsquo;m walking to Itero de Vega, about 21 km. Glad you&amp;rsquo;re on the go again, see you soon I&amp;rsquo;m sure, ultreya y suseya!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, thats where Im heading today :) yeah, Im on the way but still not feeling well, hope it wont get worse, cheewing garlic all day, poor pilgrims I meet :) see ya.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Stepan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I walked 32 km today to Fromista&amp;hellip; not sure why but really didn&amp;rsquo;t like the town before it so I walked further. Also, I got your text but not M&amp;rsquo;s, so I will email her. If you could let her know that I can&amp;rsquo;t receive her texts, that&amp;rsquo;d be cool.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday it hit me like a wrecking ball that she wasn&amp;rsquo;t here anymore&amp;hellip; sorta felt shitty and then – no joke – climbed to the top of a hill in my melancholy state, almost cried, then just started talking to the sky and myself, letting out my grievances&amp;hellip; and then the weight was lifted. As if I had finally accepted it. That’s the simple version :)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the sunset alone. Wasn&amp;rsquo;t the same of course, but the beautiful thing about sunsets is that they are always beautiful.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel ready to keep moving. Met a Korean Priest walking from Burgos who pointed me in the right direction. Told me that life doesn’t always give an immediate answer to things.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feeling good. Feet sore but not too bad. Gonna slow down tomorrow. See you soon.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ultreya y suseya,&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got to Hontanas and a fever knocked me out. Took a private room and thinking of staying for couple of days and see if I&amp;rsquo;ll recover. Just watched the sunset here. You’re right, it’s always beautiful. even when watching it alone has no sense as when shared. Prayed in a little chapel of st. Bridget at the beginning of the village for pilgrims and for M. She’s the only thing I can think about. Without her it is so empty. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a long way ahead to myself and learning a lot of things. You’re not alone in doubts, questions and all the things, dont worry bro. I got all crazy about doing The Key, to Muxia and Fisterra, I planted it in my brain so deep, felt like without it the whole camino would go in vain. Now I maybe hallucinating because of fever, but somehow I feel for a moment I stopped seeing the way and saw only the destination, I was so wrong, it’s like camino through my body is telling me to slow down and enjoy the way, for the way itself is the destination. Got to go far behind the village to get some data signal, for their wifi is not working, nor data, strange. If I was silent for couple of days it means I have no internet connection and strength to seek some :)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid to walk alone, for you’re never alone on camino. Even if you make no other friends, there are the ones you’ve already made. And don’t fear to ask yourself questions for it means that there are things yet to be asked and solved and this is what we have to do in our lives. Searching for answers is sometimes better and more giving than finding answers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultreya y suseya.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-25-2017&#34;&gt;September 25, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey Stepan,&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m keeping you in my thoughts daily and am wishing you a speedy recovery. This too is a part of the journey.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every new day continues to bring something wonderful and new. Two days ago, I had dinner with some older Americans. They enjoyed hearing my youthful stories. One of them even took my picture and had sent it to my mother&amp;hellip; it was pretty hilarious. And unexpectedly, they paid for my dinner! I was so grateful for their company and kindness. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I stayed at Albergue Santa Maria in a nice little town called Carrion de los Condes (would recommend staying there). I saw Gale there too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At night, there were nuns who started singing and playing music in my albergue. They sang a Spanish version of Hallelujah, it was incredible. Then they sang a song in Japanese! I think it surprised everyone – it definitely surprised me. It’s a beautiful language. This was truly one of the best nights. I am excited because we still have so many days ahead. It&amp;rsquo;s up to us to find the magic in each moment and in every step along the way.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I walk, my sense of love for the world grows deeper. I hope you&amp;rsquo;re continuing to grow each day on the Camino. This place&amp;hellip; this road&amp;hellip; the Way… it’s magic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking forward to hearing from ya.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, one final thing:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this thing about shadows today. Thought you might like it (this happened to be the first draft of 9: An Ode to the Road) –&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each and every day, I wake and walk with the sun behind me.&lt;br&gt;
It starts low, climbing over hillsides, rising slowly.&lt;br&gt;
It finds its temporary place along the sky, and begins to color the Meseta.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front and center a shadow grows.&lt;br&gt;
It looks at me with indifference, a mirror of my darker side –&lt;br&gt;
fear, insecurity, doubt;&lt;br&gt;
The manifestation of my inner demons.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every day, I wake and walk to confront these demons.&lt;br&gt;
However, if I fight and struggle, I hurt and suffer.&lt;br&gt;
If I push it away, I push myself away.&lt;br&gt;
I cannot hide, I cannot run,&lt;br&gt;
I can only bear witness.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only salvation is to turn off the sun. Dare I do it?&lt;br&gt;
The shadow turns abyss, immediate apocalypse.&lt;br&gt;
No. To turn off the sun is to turn from the truth;&lt;br&gt;
I would be swallowed whole.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My shadow is here,&lt;br&gt;
my shadow is me.&lt;br&gt;
As long as I walk the Way,&lt;br&gt;
it will keep me company.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must not be afraid&lt;br&gt;
I must not close my eyes&lt;br&gt;
I must continue on&lt;br&gt;
every day, rising to dawn.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every day, I wake and walk towards Santiago.&lt;br&gt;
The closer I get, the lighter I feel.&lt;br&gt;
In front of me the sun hangs low, peering over hillsides, &amp;gt;&amp;gt;descending slowly.&lt;br&gt;
The color fades from the Meseta, and my shadow is behind me.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Westward lies Santiago. I look.&lt;br&gt;
The sun has set, the dark has settled.&lt;br&gt;
A fire is growing deep inside.&lt;br&gt;
It lights the valley and shows the Way.&lt;br&gt;
I wake and walk towards the Light,&lt;br&gt;
Closer and closer to Santiago.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultreia y suseia (always higher, always further, the nuns mentioned this phrase)&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey P. So excited to read your experiences and walk to yourself. I am so happy for you bro, you deserve all the truth and acceptance coming to you. But your final observation, that&amp;rsquo;s a hard one really, sooo striking, true and beautiful. It&amp;rsquo;s like you&amp;rsquo;re stealing these words from the deepest of my soul. That&amp;rsquo;s exactly what I was telling M. in different words&amp;hellip; it is amazing how you let Camino talk to you and teach you, that&amp;rsquo;s because you&amp;rsquo;re sensitive and special. There&amp;rsquo;s not enough people like this on this world&amp;hellip; never stop being yourself, never start pretending to fulfill others&amp;rsquo; expectations. Keep on walking the Camino till your very death, always on a search for better and deeper and insightful you&amp;hellip;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now I see no shadow as I am not walking, it&amp;rsquo;s like my shadow has conquered my mind and my soul, got me trapped in the middle of my fear and when I can&amp;rsquo;t see it it&amp;rsquo;s more difficult to face it and fight it, even impossible to accept it. I feel like home, so eager to make changes yet so far away of actually doing it.. I&amp;rsquo;ll take one more day of this helplessness and then I will need to decide what next. I wish to continue, but it suddenly feels so distant and my soul feels empty.. at least I have my heart filled again and that&amp;rsquo;s a true Camino miracle to me&amp;hellip;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walk it step by step Philip and watch out for signs, even the small ones..&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Stepan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-29-2017&#34;&gt;September 29, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey Stepan,&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope you&amp;rsquo;re feeling more of yourself and on the move again. How have the past days been? What did you decide to do? How&amp;rsquo;s the fever? What have you learned?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m in Astorga right now. I&amp;rsquo;ve been walking a lot more lately - 37km, 24km and another 32km today. Feel like I should slow down, I feel too focused on reaching places instead of being a part of the journey. Life here is feeling more &amp;lsquo;normal&amp;rsquo;, so it&amp;rsquo;s harder to find the magic, but not impossible. I still look forward to each new day and to what it will bring. All of my recent joys have been through little moments – shooting stars, seeing people I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen in awhile, meeting new people who present new perspectives. The idea of teaching in Spain has been playing in my mind, especially after Leon and Astorga. We&amp;rsquo;ll see what happens.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Santiago is getting closer. Which means less time on Camino. I do feel a bit afraid of &amp;lsquo;returning&amp;rsquo; to normal life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, hope to hear from you soon.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warm blessings,&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey mate. Went to see a doctor in Castrojeriz, got ATB for really nasty bronchitis and stayed few more days, coughing my lungs out :) it was today&amp;rsquo;s morning when I braced up, said fuck the illness, this is my Camino, ATB will do their job and I shall do mine and that is walking. Made it to Poblacion de Campos and I&amp;rsquo;m on the go again. I recalled Gale saying if I break my leg I&amp;rsquo;ll continue on my knee if I break my knee I&amp;rsquo;ll crawl.. laughed and said to myself that I don&amp;rsquo;t need to finish it, I just want to.. it was tough since I decided at 9:30 :) and then got all the sun along the way and indescribable amount of dust, but got a shower now and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel that bad.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve met really great and caring hospitaleros in Castrojeviz, they were making me ginger tea for free and we were talking about running an albergue as a business, several wise insights.. also the doctor was great, no English but so caring and willing to help that we finally found understanding.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re far ahead and almost running, I see.. you still got plenty of time uh? Maybe slowing down is a good idea, unluckily for me I cannot afford it if I want to make it to Santiago as 15th Oct. is my flight back.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Castrojeriz I stumbled upon an interesting place, a hospital for soul, it was a house of some yogi man who lives there, but anyone can come in and rest, each room being a true sanctuary with paintings and quotes and places to sit, spiritual music playing silently, half color light half shadows. Behind the house was a true zen garden with sparkling water basin.. really a piece of peace.. I especially liked one quote saying &amp;ldquo;walking on the water is not a miracle, the miracle is walking on the earth&amp;rdquo; and it felt so fitting on the Camino.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not expect a miracle or magic on every kilometer on the Camino. All the miracles are already within ourselves, the Camino is just a revelation, opening our inner eyes. It is a way of ordinary people, for everyone can walk it and experience something different, so it is perfectly ok if it sometimes feels normal. And you&amp;rsquo;re right Camino will always be your part and you can benefit from it forever. Teaching in Spain?:) what happened to the Czech republic :))&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always higher, always further,&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-30-2017&#34;&gt;September 30, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, so happy to get your email. Glad you&amp;rsquo;re still on the Camino and kicking ass one step at a time. I&amp;rsquo;m sure you&amp;rsquo;ll be back to full strength sooner rather than later. It&amp;rsquo;s actually Gael by the way. Like Guy-El. Had a funny dinner with him in Leon. He taught me a lot and wouldn&amp;rsquo;t take no for an answer when he offered me half his food. &amp;ldquo;You help make my pack lighter&amp;rdquo;. Really kind and genuine guy.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I will keep my pace as that will allow me to reach FinisTerra. Meeting a lot of people who plan to go there and say it has its own magic. Met an amazing American woman who works as a therapist. She told me the whole story of why the Camino exists.. with St James and all that. Inspiring. She reminded me of an experience I had: &amp;ldquo;The Camino will give you everything you need, but not always everything you want.&amp;rdquo; At that point in time, I was feeling phased out – my head wasn’t in the game. Perhaps the Meseta had taken a toll on my body and mind. But today, walking through Galicia, I felt much more at home. The trees are a deep green and the mountains are refreshing. I then remembered one of my favorite poems and recited it in my head. And I don&amp;rsquo;t know why or how, but once again, a weight was lifted. I felt reborn. The past few days my body has become much stronger. I now feel little to no pain. I am so grateful for this new sense of physical strength.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing to meet all the necessary people along the way. And also receiving the necessary solitude too. I find so much joy and contentment in my solo walks now. It feels as if I were walking for the first time on the Camino again.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glad to hear from you. I&amp;rsquo;ll probably be in Santiago on 9 or 10 of October. Got a good feeling about it, but not setting expectations. Still trying to enjoy each and every day. Can&amp;rsquo;t believe I’ve been here for 3 weeks.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See ya soon I&amp;rsquo;m sure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-5-2017&#34;&gt;October 5, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Been receiving your texts but unable to reply for whatever reason.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glad you&amp;rsquo;re ok after going off-roading ;) whether it&amp;rsquo;s a miracle or coincidence or luck is a matter of how you want to see it. For me it&amp;rsquo;s a miracle. But don&amp;rsquo;t expect it to happen often. Just being real.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you walking barefoot now? I&amp;rsquo;m not even crazy even to try it (on my first Camino&amp;hellip; next time for sure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m in Gonzar&amp;hellip; less than 90km from Santiago. It feels surreal. Walked 31 today because I just love the Camino and this region. Letting whatever comes come, feelings and everything else. Slowing way down though. Walking 9 KM tomorrow to a well-reputed donativo tomorrow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there, I&amp;rsquo;m in Astorga. Have made over 190 over the last 6 days and it is a deadly pace, keeping me busy all day long, not exactly what I wanted.. I wish I had more time, I&amp;rsquo;d slow down to 20 a day to have time to visit churches, sit in the cafes and smell the roses :) did you meet David before Astorga? The hermit living in the ruins offering pilgrims free fruit and all the drinks? I wish I could have spent there all the afternoon.. met some hippie pilgrims there and two of them czech:) it was fun to speak czech for the first in a month..&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing like 33 really takes me all day so I&amp;rsquo;m always the last pilgrim of the day.. three days ago (that day with the raven and police) I did regular 34 of Camino plus those 7 off the track meaning 41 and arriving to Bercianos del real camino at 19h. Wanted to stay at a parroquial albergue but it was full, hospitallero laughed at me, gave me water and some fruits and told me I had 3 options.. another private albergue or a bar with accommodation or another town 7.5km further.. I felt like fainting.. went to the other albergue.. full too.. so went to the bar, it had only private rooms and only one left.. man I have never taken out those 30euros from my pocket that quick :)) had a shower and dinner and then at 21h went back to the parroquial albergue for there was supposed to be some evening ceremony.. entering the building, I saw hospitallero taking in two Russians&amp;hellip; I was literally like WTF?! Anyways went to the ceremony and it felt so rubbish, all the faces somehow empty.. man I was so pissed and felt so lonely that night.. but I guess that&amp;rsquo;s a part of the Camino too..&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No I am not walking barefoot that was just a joke for the next pilgrims. I bought new pair of shoes for the adidas were really killing me causing blisters underneath blisters.. but now I am doing first 15 in the new shoes and other 15 in sandals with my socks on and it is actually great.. freedom to the feet :) enjoy the rest of the journey, I&amp;rsquo;ll be in Santiago on 14th..&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally get the surreal feeling..&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october-7-2017&#34;&gt;October 7, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi mate how’s your Camino? Gonna be in Santiago tomorrow or so? Wish you all the best.. hope it will be the best moment of your life.. and that’s just the beginning of an endless row of best days…&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, looks like you&amp;rsquo;re having fun in the photo! I&amp;rsquo;m glad.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I will be in Santiago around noon or so. I&amp;hellip; I feel a plethora of emotions&amp;hellip; sadness that it will soon be over, joy and gratitude for having been on this journey, love that I&amp;rsquo;ve met so many amazing people. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I can sleep tonight. It&amp;rsquo;s as if a knot has tied itself a million times over in my stomach. That&amp;rsquo;s partly why I haven&amp;rsquo;t written much. Already started tearing up walking through Arzua thinking about it today, about the memories, the people, the personal breakthroughs. Not sure what to expect. I have no expectations. Whatever happens I hope to have the strength to let it be free and expressed. Met a wonderful pair of brother and sister today. They gave me strength, especially the brother. Amazing because even though he&amp;rsquo;s 49, I&amp;rsquo;ve never felt so at ease with an older guy. He’s young in spirit. Made a deep connection walking with him after his sister had to take a taxi due to knee issues. Talked about love, the magic of the Camino, life lessons. He shared a secret with me&amp;hellip; one that he only has ever told to his sister. Really made me feel special&amp;hellip; said he felt a kinship with me. Honestly, it felt like I was walking with an older version of myself, a much wiser man yet we shared so much in common – quiet, reserved, calm. Can&amp;rsquo;t even describe it, he was really who I needed at that moment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways I&amp;rsquo;m doing&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m doing. Ready to walk, ready and not ready for Santiago. I will do it alone, but knowing that I&amp;rsquo;m never truly alone. It is the gift the Camino has given me – a love that allows me to walk with joy, even in solitude. Thanks for checking in. The timing is perfect. I hope you&amp;rsquo;re well. I would be lying if I didn&amp;rsquo;t want you guys with me at Santiago. But this is the gift, this is what Camino is asking me to do, and I accept the invitation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something tells me I will be better for it. Also, I have a feeling that I will see everyone again.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am happy for you bro and I shall walk with you tomorrow to Santiago in my thoughts. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be more happier if we arrived there the three of us. But that would be what I&amp;rsquo;d want too&amp;hellip; and Camino gives you only what your soul need, not what you want, remember?;)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a gift, yet deserved. You have walked your camino humbly with your heart open and with joy, a true pilgrim, not some kind of a tourist that it seems I get to meet these days..&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so do it again, walk with your heart open and embrace whatever comes your way.. I am sure it will be good&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have one last week of walking and cannot deny that I&amp;rsquo;m too starting to think about the approaching end and feeling fears of getting back to the grey of old life&amp;hellip; what if no change comes.. no, that&amp;rsquo;s not gonna happen. I will make changes and I won&amp;rsquo;t think about it till the end of my camino and will walk it more humbly too. I am so glad that I can still be here.. that I stopped only to start over and not to quit..&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, camino&amp;rsquo;s still calling&amp;hellip; and we shall answer this call&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wish you the greatest walk ever though I am not gonna see your eyes when you get there.. but I&amp;rsquo;ll see them another time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Stepan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>14: Letters to a Camino Soulmate</title>
        <link>/posts/letters-soulmate/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/letters-soulmate/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;p&gt;These are the emails Marieke and I wrote to each other after she was gone. They might give you a better picture of my Camino experience. Writing to her was always a highlight. Sorry for the grammar. Wrote every letter on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-21-2017&#34;&gt;September 21, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just realized I did not give you my email. Safe travels! Thank you for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-23-2017&#34;&gt;September 23, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, as I walked away from Burgos, it clicked: you were gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I had reached my destination, I went to the church and sat in silence for awhile – I even prayed! My mind ran through all of our moments and memories, like a broken record player… I was drowning under the weight of an emotional tsunami.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I climbed a hill until the people were nothing more than ants. I stayed for awhile, gazing at the sky and clouds, trying to make sense of my emotions, trying to fill the maw your absence has left. Thoughts came and went, feelings mixed and churned. Time moved at the pace of a snail.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then an odd thing happened: I began talking to myself. It was like the unconscious part of me had finally connected the dots; I started to laugh at myself and began shouting at the sky until I reached this profound state of peace, of liberation. There was nothing left but clarity and stillness. I felt free, weightless.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote that bus note believing I had already accepted the fact that you were leaving. Yet, it was only when I admitted to myself that I missed you did I find some semblance of tranquility.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the sunset. It hid behind a thicket of clouds and colored the sky a deep and dark red. I smiled because it felt like the universe had given me peace. It knew I was ready to let go. The crimson sky faded into night. Symbolic right? Red is your favorite color.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, there are no sad or lonely feelings. And it&amp;rsquo;s not because I don&amp;rsquo;t miss you anymore, rather, I am filled with gratitude each time my mind replays a memory. I look forward to the day that we cross paths again. I know it&amp;rsquo;s not the last time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
-Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-25-2017&#34;&gt;September 25, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dearest, dearest Phil!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so sorry for giving you a sign of life only now&amp;hellip; When I took place on the bus, I felt a hole in my heart that was so big that I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t bear it. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t write. It was just too painful. I missed you in everything, I could hear you laughter and your jokes in everything, even though you were not here I would hear your interesting questions and opinions continuously in my mind. I can still see you ahead of me, with the orange water bottle swinging in your hand&amp;hellip;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here in Belgium life continues, the beginning of the semester is extremely busy. Most people take little interest in the fact that I lived for three weeks on the Camino and barely know what it means. My friends do their utmost best to listen, but they were not there with you; they cannot understand. I feel like I would need more time to contemplate and maybe have some mourning process too, but life allows me only some stolen moments. When I walk through my garden and I look up, I can see the same stars as you, I see sunlight playing a color game with the leaves of the trees just as they existed in Spain, I hear the same birds as you. They are like calls from a faraway universe. I hear you in them&amp;hellip; The pain of missing you is getting better day by day. It is the grace of life: everything changes, everything flows, the good and the bad. What doesn&amp;rsquo;t wear off, is that I feel incredibly close to you. The initial hole in my heart is now filled with your warm presence, you are with me all day and I know that you are one of these people I will be carrying forever.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that your experience on that mountain was probably very similar to mine. There are no words to explain the perfect beauty and mercy of such a moment&amp;hellip; We cannot create them alone, they are partly also given to us by something greater than us. You cannot explain, but simply know that something in you has thoroughly changed. I came very close to crying again, when I read about your experience, I was immensely grateful that your listening to Camino had led you also to such an experience. Your writing about it was so beautiful that I actually printed it and hung it on my wall..&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start to see more and more why I had to return to Belgium. I think it had something to do partly with finding a real and human balance in my life, but there is more. It is not very correct to say that I just left Belgium for Camino. Rather, I fled from it. I had been facing repeating patterns in relationships for years, and had just entered a next one that was actually very harmful to me but I lacked the strength to end it. This Camino, and especially you and my mountain experience, have given me true love to myself. I cannot longer do things that are harmful to me&amp;hellip; I feel so, so strong now&amp;hellip; I now want to learn to feel love, I want to learn to love others. I feel that many things in me have ripened during Camino, up to a level where they can start to give fruits. I notice that there is more life in the bonds I have with other people. It gives me hope, for I have feared for so long that I was a mistake of nature – born without feelings. The only relation that is still really fucked up, is the one with my parents. Emotionally, I feel a thousand miles away from them, and it only gets worse. They have no time for me, I am too proud by now to run after them, the result is that we barely know each other anymore. It hurts me a lot. It feels like they care very little for me&amp;hellip;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this is probably a strange mail to you, more some concatenation of random topics.. Writing is not my strength, and I lack the patience to reread what I wrote. Sorry! :)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please, tell me more about how things are going on Camino.. if you talk about it, it feels to me almost as if I were also there.. What is Camino sending you at the moment? Who are the people you meet? Are you walking the Meseta, do you like it? And.. what was your miracle today?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I send you an incredibly warm hug, and all the love that I can!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
-Marieke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-26-2017&#34;&gt;September 26, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My heart totally skipped a beat when I saw your message in my inbox. I&amp;rsquo;m really happy to hear from you. I enjoyed your concatenation of thoughts! It was sporadic and spontaneous. Keep writing from your heart.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day I left Burgos, I met a Korean Catholic Priest near the edge of the city. There was a warm presence about him, something friendly and inviting, like a hot cup of tea. He strolled up to me and we started talking about religion, our families, and why we were walking the Camino. Then he asked a very interesting question: what are the most important things in your life? And for some reason, I had no immediate answer. I felt a bit guilty. He responded, &amp;ldquo;Ah, see you&amp;rsquo;re not like most people. They usually say something right away: friends, family, work. But you didn&amp;rsquo;t. Why?&amp;rdquo; I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure why. He then said that it was ok not to know, and better to continue asking Why. Why is family important? Why this.. and that&amp;hellip; we left the question unanswered. Again, he asked why I was here. I told him I was looking for direction&amp;hellip; for purpose. He replied Why?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He finally gave an answer after I gave some more inconclusive replies: &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s simple, ask why and follow the answer your heart gives. You have a good heart. Listen to it. It knows. It&amp;rsquo;s ok to keep asking too and not get an answer. Ask why.&amp;rdquo; He then asked to take a selfie with me, and he walked away.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I find myself asking Why as I consider all of the things I&amp;rsquo;ve ever wanted to be: artist, journalist, radio host, writer, English teacher, university professor, counselor, therapist, physical therapist, psychiatrist, lifestyle designer, coach, school psychologist&amp;hellip; these sorts of roles are deeply human-centric&amp;hellip; I seem to require intimate human connection in my work. I can see myself as a healer of sorts, as someone who walks / guides people through life. I&amp;rsquo;m still asking Why.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past Sunday, I stopped in Carrion de los Condes at Albergue Santa Maria. It was like our first night in the donativo. The other pilgrims and I sat in a large rectangular formation and shared our names and motivations for walking the Camino. The stories were moving. A Korean woman diagnosed with Parkinson&amp;rsquo;s disease had decided to walk the Camino to fight against it, to prove to everyone around her that she would not let the disease consume her life. Her hand was trembling as she used her phone to translate her message into English and Spanish. I was on the verge of tears.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others walked for self-redemption, for answers to life&amp;rsquo;s biggest questions, for love. I shared that I came in search of direction, but that I have received so much more – myself, my voice, my heart, joy, sadness, gratitude&amp;hellip; and of course, I mentioned how I met you, Matilde, and Franca, all over a cup of tea&amp;hellip; I don&amp;rsquo;t know if there&amp;rsquo;s a better story than ours. Anyways, amid the words being lost in translation, the universal language of music beckoned. The nuns started playing songs on the guitar, and we sang! Like a choir, we sang a Spanish rendition of Hallelujah&amp;hellip; and then the nuns sang a Japanese song for one of the Japanese pilgrims&amp;hellip; what a beautiful language! These nuns were not your ordinary nuns. I slept with a smile that night.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been walking with an older woman from Columbia. Her English isn&amp;rsquo;t the best, but she understands what I&amp;rsquo;m saying, for the most part&amp;hellip; maybe she&amp;rsquo;s being nice and only laughs at my own jokes because I laugh at them. I almost told her your squirrel joke, but I forgot some of it. Sorry.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh! Yesterday, I met a really cool French girl. We made some small talk and I walked her to the end of the village. I had a feeling I would see her again. And sure enough, today, while I was unpacking, I saw her enter my albergue – she ended up in the same room as me! We were talking about books, and I asked if she had any in English. She said one&amp;hellip; guess which? THE POWER OF NOW. The only book you were carrying, she happened to be carrying too. Crazy, right?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, tomorrow morning&amp;hellip; at 4 AM&amp;hellip;. I&amp;rsquo;m walking with her and her friend, Morgan, to catch some shooting stars. Not sure what I&amp;rsquo;m getting myself into, but this is the opportunity that has presented itself, so I will take it and adventure on.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meseta stretches far, but it is beautiful. One day, I walked 17km straight. There were no places to stop for a break. It was brutal, but the sunrise was nice, as was the landscape. Many would say the meseta is a bland belt of dust and wheat, but there is so much life in the trees, air, and grass. It&amp;rsquo;s also much easier to notice a change of color when the fields are all a singular shade of gold! No blackberries though, sadly.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Missing that squirrelly girl obsessed with blackberries. I think she gave me some of her magic though. I had the “Best Coffee Ever” yesterday, so smooth and creamy, I could taste the love.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have so much more to say, but it&amp;rsquo;s getting late and I&amp;rsquo;ll be up at 4:00am. I wish I could just teleport to you, with a cup of your favorite coffee in my hand and share everything in my head. There&amp;rsquo;s so so much.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re not a mistake of nature. And you’re more than capable of loving. I&amp;rsquo;ve felt it. We&amp;rsquo;re all screwed up in our own way&amp;hellip; maybe we just need to find the people who love us anyways. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what to say about you and your parents&amp;hellip; That isn&amp;rsquo;t an easy thing to live with. You feel it so much more than any words can describe, or that anyone can truly relate to to be helpful. All I can offer is a listening ear and an open heart.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s so much more to say, but not enough time. I know you know the Camino struggles. Anyways, from the wholeness of my heart, sleep well, dream on.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-27-2017&#34;&gt;September 27, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I walked 38km&amp;hellip; I am in Leon with the sorest of feet, but the biggest of smiles.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine you are buried beneath a mound of books, bones, and cadavers. Make sure to see the light of day. Don’t forget to do you, to maintain balance, to make your art! Busyness is the enemy of time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s strange, there are moments when I feel that you are still walking and talking to me. You tell me to slow down, to enjoy the little things (because they&amp;rsquo;re actually the big things), to relish the company of nature. I miss enjoying these things with you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I will sleep well tonight. This was one of my toughest yet most rewarding days, full of many wonderful blessings, people, and lessons. I&amp;rsquo;m dozing off now, twilight calls, that eternal place of peaceful nothingness. Each day still feels so fresh and new. I am always pleasantly surprised.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
-Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-1-2017&#34;&gt;October 1, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galicia is beautiful. I feel so at home and energized being surrounded by the green vegetation and high mountains. Wish you could feel the cool, mountainous air.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A miracle: after 2 days of hip, ankle, and achilles pain, the Camino seems to have given me new legs. As I was walking, the pain suddenly disappeared. I was freaking out and telling everyone around me what had happened. They said I should be grateful.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Random note: I&amp;rsquo;ve memorized Wild Geese. It was on a day when I was feeling a bit blue, melancholy and lonely. It&amp;rsquo;s strange, even though I feel this deep love for myself and life, loneliness and sadness seem to always be accompanying me, like shadows. I suppose that means I&amp;rsquo;m human. But I know the feelings will pass, like the rush of a cool summer breeze. Anyways, during one of my breaks, I sat and read Wild Geese at least 5 times, until I memorized it. Now each and every time I recite it, I feel so much joy… this line always brings me to tears: &amp;ldquo;whoever you are, no matter how lonely / the world offers itself to your imagination, / calls to you like the wild geese, harsh and exciting - over and over announcing your place in the family of things.&amp;rdquo; It makes me feel at peace,connected with the universe.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I sent some pictures to my parents. Their immediate response was: why aren&amp;rsquo;t you in the pictures? To which I replied Because I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be, it&amp;rsquo;s a personal reason related to why I am on the Camino. They then said How do we know these are yours then&amp;hellip; reading that made me furious. Did they not trust me? Did they still see me as a helpless child, unable to make his own decisions, unable to have his own feelings and beliefs? I felt disconnected and misunderstood. Conceptually, I understood their response – they’re parents. But emotionally, I lost control.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that moment, I didn&amp;rsquo;t love them. And then I hated myself for feeling that. I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have. Sometimes, we just lose control and say and think things we don’t mean. Still, I turned my phone off and walked around Astorga to clear my head. Then I ran into two of my friends. They helped me to process and make peace with the situation. Sadly, one of them is leaving soon. I felt a true kinship with him because he was so interested in life. He showed me the value of simply listening and watching. A true photographer.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final bit of update: so… I refunded my flight to Amsterdam from Paris. Guess where I’m heading instead? I just ask that you be home October 14th&amp;hellip; I really wanted to surprise you, but I know you said to tell you in advance if I were to visit&amp;hellip; that&amp;rsquo;s not to say that I&amp;rsquo;m visiting, but maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll be in the area on that day&amp;hellip; possibly…&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok. Assuming you&amp;rsquo;re still buried under a bag of bodies and books, I&amp;rsquo;ll bring a shovel.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve become addicted to Spanish milk. It is my lifeblood. I think it contributed to my newfound legs.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Santiago nears, I feel a plethora of emotions, and some sense of expectation. I guess it&amp;rsquo;s hard not to have expectations since everyone is talking about how beautiful and amazing it is. Still, I’m trying to take it day by day. Each day is so special and full of life. I will let Santiago come when it comes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-2-2017&#34;&gt;October 2, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m trying for a few days now to find some time to write back decently (and no, not because I&amp;rsquo;m buried in books :p), but this cannot wait: I&amp;rsquo;M SO VERY EXCITED THAT YOU COME! :)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just tell me, which days exactly will you be in Belgium? I&amp;rsquo;ll provide your fifteen star hotel, of course! :D&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
–Marieke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-3-2017&#34;&gt;October 3, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No rush to reply! And 15 out of 100? I expected more from Belgium ;) I will be there Oct. 14-15, and leave to Prague the night of the 15th.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
-Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-6-2017&#34;&gt;October 6, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it seems that I am closing the distance between me and Santiago. With less than 55 km to go, I will be there on Sunday, probably around noon. I&amp;rsquo;m trying my damndest not to count the kilometers, to focus on the present moment, but it&amp;rsquo;s difficult! I need to keep my head in the game and to remember to actually taste my coffee&amp;hellip;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past week or so (really, since Burgos), I&amp;rsquo;ve walked alone, which allows for the free flow of my thoughts. They come and go in all shapes and forms, some really random, others more anxious and fearful. But they are just that, thoughts. They are not me. I know this because my mood instantly shifts the moment I notice the sound of my footsteps against the stones, the chirping of the birds, the rustling of leaves.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been having these second winds on my walk, sudden bursts of energy that drive me forward with the force of a raging river. I feel free and limitless in this state&amp;hellip; I stop noticing thoughts, I feel outside of my body, I am attuned to my surroundings… I am high on life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Been wondering if what the Camino has given me is the gift of solitude. Because only in solitude do you hear the sound of your own voice. Then it&amp;rsquo;s a matter of knowing which sound is your mind, and which is your heart. As of late, it&amp;rsquo;s becoming easier to hear the latter, &amp;ldquo;This is your heart / can you feel it, / can you feel it?&amp;rdquo; (Bastille - Laura Palmer). To clearly hear my own voice, that was one of my intentions for coming to the Camino. I miss you, Franca, Matilde, and S; I miss having wonderful people like you guys to share these experiences with. Yet, there is another kind of solitary joy that I&amp;rsquo;ve been experiencing every day. I find it sometimes in the darkest of corners, right when I need it most, and I sit and smile and laugh wildly at myself, at something I wrote in my journal, at something I drew or something that happened during the day. (I passed two people and yelled, &amp;ldquo;Woo! Another day on the Way!&amp;rdquo; They loved it.). In reflection of moments like these, I know the Camino is asking me to reach Santiago alone.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel so strong. I have an insatiable desire to learn, to taste, to live, to start the next part of my life journey.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, I think this will be my last update until I see you. I&amp;rsquo;m wicked excited to see that smile and to hear more squirrel jokes. By the way, been listening to Leonard Cohen, and I think Suzanne is my current favorite. Check out the acoustic version of &amp;ldquo;The Woods&amp;rdquo; by Hollow Coves. Best listened to under a tree, illuminated by starlight. See you soon.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
–Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-7-2017&#34;&gt;October 7, 2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not so good at writing and I don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy it as much as you do, which is probably one of the reasons why I postpone writing back everyday. But every e-mail of you manages to bring me to this very thin border between laughing and crying out of pure joy and gratitude. Gratitude that you have become so immensely strong and radiantly beautiful that I can feel it all the 2300km to Leuven&amp;hellip; You are vibrant with life, you are so pure, I just can&amp;rsquo;t wait to see you. I am counting the days, I am telling everyone that I meet that you will be coming next week, and it&amp;rsquo;s one of the reasons that make me randomly smile during the day. Actually I just came upstairs to my room after cooking with my friends and sitting with them for a while&amp;hellip; they were telling me that I definitely changed after Camino. That I&amp;rsquo;m more playful and energetic, that I enjoy even more to make stupid jokes and that I look (alas) even younger.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And still, there is some fear in me that you&amp;rsquo;ll be disappointed when you see me back&amp;hellip; Time on the camino has made you grow, I wish so much I could have made this journey too that it physically hurts me. Instead, real life continued for me – and even though I&amp;rsquo;m living life in a much more balanced way than I ever did, I am stagnating in growth&amp;hellip; I still wonder whether medicine is right for me, if it cannot allow me to grow further. Right now my plan is to finish my year, walk the Camino again and then decide. Sometimes I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m the only one awake in this world, the medical world. I see so many sleeping people and I would like to wake them all, but they just don&amp;rsquo;t listen, they only think I&amp;rsquo;m weird :) Which, to me, is a complement of course!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for writing to me, Phil, even when I don&amp;rsquo;t answer&amp;hellip; you have no idea how much I enjoy every word of your beautiful writing. You have such a talent&amp;hellip; When you come here, I&amp;rsquo;ll show you that I put some of your writing at the door of my room, to be able to read it every day :) Everything you write is so true, it comes right from your heart, and my heart recognizes ancient truth and pure joy in it, which is a lovely warm feeling.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love it that you discovered Cohen! He&amp;rsquo;s a real poet, someone who understood life. You&amp;rsquo;ll discover that at any time of your life, there&amp;rsquo;s always a song of his that guides you through. Thank you for the song! It went right to my playlist ;) Here&amp;rsquo;s a spanish poem to you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caminante no hay Camino&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caminante, son tus huellas&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;el camino y nada más;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caminante, no hay camino,&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;se hace camino al andar.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al andar se hace el camino,&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;y al volver la vista atrás&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;se ve la senda que nunca&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;se ha de volver a pisar.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caminante no hay camino&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;sino estelas en la mar.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wayfarer, there is no path&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wayfarer, the only way&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your footprints and no other.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wayfarer, there is no way.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make your way by going farther.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By going farther, make your way&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till looking back at where you’ve wandered,&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You look back on that path you may&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not set foot on from now onward.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wayfarer, there is no way;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only wake-trails on the waters.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I send you a big hug, and cannot wait to make it a real one…&lt;br&gt;
–Marieke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>13: The Iron Cross</title>
        <link>/posts/ironcross/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/ironcross/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-1st-2017-day-25&#34;&gt;October 1st, 2017 - Day 25&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dawn. A ridge of silhouettes and gray clouds against a colorless expanse. A string of headlamps clambering up a mountain. At the top, an iron cross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The autumnal air invigorates me, my legs are weightless. I pass several pilgrims on my way up. Shanti is up ahead. I reach him and he smiles at me. We climb through the dark together, delighting in the thrill of the ascent. The Spaniard and I are at home here in the highlands of Galicia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several pilgrims are gathered around a swell of stones. A wooden pillar protrudes from its center, and on top sits an iron cross. Perhaps it represents the relationship between earth and heaven, humanity and God. I’m entertained by the thought, but can’t help and feel a peculiar air of mysticism. The pilgrims gaze skyward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I move closer and scan the assemblage of rocks and tokens. Necklaces, bracelets, beads, crumbled notes, a mangled hiking shoe, faded photographs, a teddy bear. On a rock, “CAMO AND MORELLO, 2017.” A woman in a headscarf approaches the altar, kneels, and sets the picture of who I think is a loved one between a rock and the foot of the pillar. She laces her fingers together, bows her head, and begins to cry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to legend, pilgrims will carry a rock with them from the beginning of their journey and place it here at the base of the cross. The rock symbolizes the sins of the pilgrim, and the act of leaving it behind is supposed to clean the slate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see it differently. To me, the rock represents all of the extra, unnecessary weight we carry with us through life – bitterness, resentment, fear, negativity, cynicism. The rock weighs us down. It prevent us from truly enjoying life, from tasting the joy and freedom inherent in being present. It chains us to the unforgiving, unrelenting storm of our past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the rock behind symbolizes our growth, it is the movement from there to here, an act of profound surrender. It is a letting go of the overplayed narratives that prevent us from creating a new story, from being who we want to be, from growing. It is the ultimate form of self-acceptance, and moving on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have a rock, but I did have my California license plate. I wasn’t planning on leaving it, but the moment called: its expiration date was October 2017, and today was the first day of October 2017. It was Sunday, a day of reflection, beginnings, and endings. The plate was me, the old me. The struggle to find direction after college. The shitty first job. The search for belonging and meaning. The failed relationships. The insecurities. The fear of the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write Matilde’s, Franca’s, Stepan’s, and Marieke’s name on the plate. They had brought out and continue to foster the best parts of me. I place the plate against the base of the pillar, dismount from the heap, and walk on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/cross.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>12: Journal Entries from Day 22 - 24</title>
        <link>/posts/journal22-24/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/journal22-24/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-28-2017-day-22&#34;&gt;September 28, 2017 - Day 22&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be yourself–&lt;br&gt;
Easy to say, hard to do.&lt;br&gt;
What we think is not ours.&lt;br&gt;
What we believe is shaped by others.&lt;br&gt;
The only thing we own is&lt;br&gt;
what we feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our inner compass, the way we connect with&lt;br&gt;
The outer world; only we can see and touch and&lt;br&gt;
Feel the way we do. Never lose it.&lt;br&gt;
Never let it go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met Enrico and Sia today. Italian Photographer, Jewish Psychologist. Good vibes, good conversation. Talked about the nature of identity and self, meditation, instant gratification, feelings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to feel? To listen to what our heart has to say. –Sia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strangest thing happened while I was talking with Sia: the pain in my legs had suddenly disappeared! The sharpness in my hip, the knot in my foot, they vanished like a puff of air. I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining, but what exactly happened? It seems like the Camino has given me new legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got lost. We were supposed to stop in Hospital de Orbigo, but ended up at Villadangos del Paramo. We’re staying at an albergue called La Casa de Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s Enrico’s birthday, but he’s decided to cook for &lt;em&gt;us&lt;/em&gt;. Risotto. I provided the wine, Sia the cake. A lovely American woman from California and a guy around my age from Washington D.C. joined our celebration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enrico is cool. He’s genuine, contemplative, and expressive with his emotions and thoughts, all the while possessing a humble confidence that I truly admire. He was fascinated by what I had to say about psychology, meditation, and the creative process. I was captivated by the way he described the art of photography and his prior journey into the Swiss Alps. I wish he wasn&amp;rsquo;t leaving tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-29-2017-day-23&#34;&gt;September 29, 2017 - Day 23&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Meseta makes up ⅓ of the Camino. It’s a barren wasteland of wheat, desert, and more wheat. Not much to see, but it’s peaceful. Though I understand why people complain about it, or skip it entirely. The roads stretch for miles; it’s hot and arid; any sign of life appears to have been sucked dry. But what is a pilgrimage without a little bit of suffering?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made it to the city of Astorga. Looking forward to the greenery, hills, and mountains of the Galicia region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s beautiful here. There’s a large park nearby. I had a picnic with Mariam, a German girl who had only started her Camino a few days ago in Leon. She’s reserved and somewhat aloof. But nice. Wonder what was on her mind. We took a nap during Siesta. It’s a part of the Spanish culture – don’t work too hard, relax. America needs more Siesta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sia and Enrico arrived later in the day. I found them in the kitchen cooking couscous. We had dinner together. It was Enrico’s last day on the Camino. I’ve only known him for a day, but he feels like a brother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the evening, Enrico and I went to the park. The sound of snare drums, horns, and brass instruments filled the air. There were children playing music, perhaps practicing for a performance. They looked like they were having a lot of fun. Enrico took some pictures. We sat and listened for awhile, cherishing the moment. I felt happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for your presence, Enrico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-30-2017-day-24&#34;&gt;September 30, 2017 - Day 24&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in the Galicia region now. Mountains, vegetation, life surrounds me. I feel at home, up in the clouds and mountains. I saw a blackberry bush. It reminded me of M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met an energetic, charming American named Jackie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hey! You remind me of another beautiful young man I met just a few days ago.” I blushed – I am not so used to receiving compliments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back home, she’s a therapist. Said this was the first time in her life that she was taking care of herself and not others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s so amazing to be here. I haven’t thought about life back home at all! I’ve just been so focused on trying to take it all in, you know? Oh, look at that flower! Beautiful huh? My husband gets worried so he texts me every night, but I keep saying &amp;lsquo;I’m fine, I’m fine!&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A few days ago, I met this young woman from Australia – she looks about your age – who had decided to walk because her mother had recently died. She was so lost, she just wanted the pain to stop. On a whim she packed her things and started walking through Australia. And now she&amp;rsquo;s here. Still walking.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But here’s the crazy part: she met a guy from Switzerland here. The kicker is that his mother had also recently died! And he was walking for the same reasons – all the way from Switzerland! Is that destiny or what? Now they&amp;rsquo;re inseparable. They&amp;rsquo;ve been walking together ever since.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Camino - there’s just something special about it. I believe in God, and I believe that he put them together for a reason. But, you could also say it was the Camino. It had provided them with what they needed most: a person who could understand their pain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in Foncebadón. Met Terra and Kristen. Terra is from Nevada, and Kristen is from California. Also met a guy from Northern Spain, Shanti – he’s really cool. Shanti and I share a love for travel, mountains, the world. He’s a photographer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner was absolutely ludicrous. The hospitalero was a total control freak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In donation-based albergues, pilgrims are expected to assist with dinner preparations and cleaning. But here, people were cutting vegetables in the “wrong” way. The hospitalero scoffed at them, then deicded to cut the vegetables himself; things had to be &lt;em&gt;perfecto&lt;/em&gt;. All-or-nothing. Apparently, no one was doing anything right, so he ended up preparing the entire dinner for all 18 of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was hilarious but Terra and Kristen didn’t – they had been reprimanded by our fellow perfectionist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we finished dinner, the hospitalero invited everyone to have &lt;em&gt;chupitos&lt;/em&gt; – shots – at the only bar in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terra: “I thought he hated us, but now he’s buying everyone shots.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/shots.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>11: A Sea of Stars</title>
        <link>/posts/stars/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/stars/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;day-21&#34;&gt;Day 21&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4:30am. I inch out from my sleeping bag like a slug, careful not to disturb the others in the room, pack my things and head downstairs. Pauline and Morgan are already awake. We’re late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eyes are crusty. I wolf down a prepacked sandwich – chorizo and cheese – with yogurt. Pauline makes us some coffee. Bland, but it will do. Shoes on, rucksacks shouldered, we’re on the move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cold pierces through my layers. A creeping wave of goosebumps shivers down my spine. I’m in shorts because I&amp;rsquo;ve lost my pants. Ridiculous. My feet are sore. It takes thirty minutes of walking before the endorphins kick in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pauline is several paces ahead of Morgan and I. We exit town and walk into the twilight, guided by nothing more than the faint glow of a city encapsulated by a narrow crescent of light, a dim lantern flickering in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pauline disappears into the darkness. We know she’s ahead, somewhere, but we don’t see her – we can’t. It’s just Morgan and I. We&amp;rsquo;ve decided not to use our flashlights in order to see the stars. Flickers of movement perturb the corners of my vision. Rock and gravel crunch beneath the soles of our shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re walking on a long and narrow road alongside an empty highway. Two cars drive by and shock us with their blinding highbeams. Morgan is close. I wonder if she’s scared of the dark. In the eastern quadrant of the sky, my eyes catch a streak of light. I lean my head back and gaze into the dark ocean, scanning. A shooting star. Another blazes by; I catch it this time. Another, then another. I make a wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to teach some English to Morgan. States. They’re like how countries are divided in Europe. California, where I’m from, could definitely be 3 countries in Europe. She’s shy to speak, but tries anyways. She&amp;rsquo;s 22. She has an older brother. She graduated from university two years ago and works as a nurse in France. She’s currently on vacation. She likes dogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tell her I have to stop and pee. She seems confused, but quickly realizes what I had meant as I scurried behind a tree. She continues on. Once I finish, I catch up and we walk in silent admiration of the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 20 minutes or so, she has to pee too. She tells me I can continue, so I do. I then catch up to Pauline. She teaches me some colors in French: noir, blanc, vert, bleu - black white green blue. I parrot them back and she laughs. “It’s cute,” she says. Morgan catches up, and we continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Some time in the afternoon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“TIMOOTHY!!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I turn around and spot my two favorite Germans, now on bicycles: Franca and Matilde. Matilde tells me her feet aren’t in great of shape, so they&amp;rsquo;ve bought bikes to compensate. They’re headed to Leon. Morgan, Pauline and I consider following them. It’s an extra 10 kilometers on top of the 27 we’ve already walked. There’s a sharp pain in my hip joint and achilles, but we decide to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10 kilometers later we’re in Leon. The height of hills and street curbs have become insurmountable. I wince in agony as I drag my legs through the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reach the albergue. 38 kilometers total according to my FitBit, the longest distance I’ve walked yet. No Franca and Matilde though. They must be elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dining room I see Gael, a Belgian I had met about a week ago in another albergue. I tell him how far I’ve walked today. He grins and replies, “Well, if you’re tired your face doesn’t show it!” Gael has a great attitude. “When I am climbing these hills, I imagine that I am a bird flying over them; what is pain but weakness leaving the body; no matter what decision you make, you make it the best one; just smile and keep walking!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From his rucksack, he pulls out a large container of potato salad, a foot-long baguette, and a box filled with chocolate pastries. “Have you eaten yet?” Pointing to the food, “Here. Eat. Pilgrims need to eat after a long days walk, especially you. You need to eat so that you can become strong.” I tell him it’s too much to offer, that he’s way too kind. “No, no! You are helping me because there’s no way I can finish all of this. Also, you are helping me keep my pack very light. Please, eat.” I resist no longer, thank him, and feast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two days prior, I had found a stray T-shirt in my albergue. It was dark navy-blue with the picture of a bull on its front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my meal with Gael, I showered and put the shirt on. I then went to write in a small cafe. While scribbling something down, an older American approached me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hello. That’s a cool shirt. Where did you get it?” he asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I found it a few days ago in my albergue. It was hanging from the corner of a chair. Everyone had already left, so I decided to take it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, you might not believe it, but that’s my shirt! It was a gift from my daughter for my birthday. She got it in Madrid.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Really? Well, you can totally have it back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Are you sure? You can keep it if you need it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah of course! It’s your shirt. I don’t need it. I’m sure it means a lot to you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you. It’s unbelievable that you&amp;rsquo;ve found it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran back to my albergue, threw on a different shirt, and returned to the man. He asked to take a picture of me holding the shirt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, I ran into him again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I messaged my family about what just happened, and they just couldn’t believe it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/sea.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>10: Journal Entries from Day 17 - 20</title>
        <link>/posts/journal17-20/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/journal17-20/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-23-2017-day-17&#34;&gt;September 23, 2017 - Day 17&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are always on the cusp of collapse and redemption. Do we choose to rise, or do we settle and fall?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stories = meaning. The mind is a meaning-making machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stories have the power to change people’s lives, and we are the narrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, a group of Americans invited me to their table at dinner. They were much older than me and asked a lot of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I am walking alone. No, it’s not so bad. My feet are ok, I don’t have any blisters. Yeah, I get that often (“You smile a lot!”). Well, my parents weren’t too fond of the idea, but they couldn’t have stopped me even if they had wanted to. Eh, I don’t know if it’s brave, maybe naive and reckless is more accurate. I enjoy the freedom, the simplicity, the clarity of mind. I’ve been learning a lot about myself. Yeah, my friends are supportive. And funny you should ask, I met this girl from Belgium…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh my god. That is such a cute story. Are you going to visit her?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t thought of it. Maybe I should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Phil, we had such a great time with you. You are a remarkable young man. Don’t worry about dinner, it’s on us. And tell your Mom that you met a bunch of older Americans, and that they’ve adopted you. Actually––.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer asked for my Mom’s number and sent her a picture of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Jennifer, Molly, Rex, Carlos, and Jackie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-24-2017-day-18&#34;&gt;September 24, 2017 - Day 18&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short day, 21 kilometers. It’s Sunday. I’ve stopped at the endearing municipal of Carrión de los Condes. Checked-in at the Santa Maria albergue. Three doors down toward the main street is the church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thought about what Molly said last night, about visiting M. It’s audacious, but what the hell. As if the Camino wasn&amp;rsquo;t already bold enough. Why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I called Transavia and asked if they could refund my flight to Amsterdam. Luckily, they did. I now have a bus ticket from Paris to Belgium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I returned from the grocery store, all of the pilgrims in the albergue were situated around the staircase in the living room. Four nuns were sitting in the front, one with a guitar. We took turns introducing ourselves and telling our reasons for walking the Camino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was riveted by the story of an elderly Korean woman. She spoke into her translator and it said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A few years ago, I was diagnosed with Parkinson’s Disease, but I wasn’t ready to lose my body. I chose to walk the Camino because of it. I wanted to prove everyone wrong. My family said I was crazy. But so far, I have walked for 300 kilometers, alone. I feel so alive, and I know that I am not alone because God is at my side. He continues to give me strength.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nuns ended the night with music. They played their guitar and sang songs in English, Spanish, and Japanese! I was enchanted. These weren’t your traditional nuns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wondering how Stepan is doing. Hope he’s feeling better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-25-2017-day-19&#34;&gt;September 25, 2017 - Day 19&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An observation: Every day that we wake and walk, the sun begins behind us, leaving us with only our shadow. This shadow represents our fears, insecurities, and struggles, the things we hesitate to look at in the eye; in essence, our inner demons. We wake each day to confront these demons as we walk towards Santiago. But we cannot get rid of them, because then we must get rid of the sun; no sun and the shadow becomes an engulfing abyss. Rather, we must fully accept the shadow, see it as it is, and nourish it with love. It will always be there so long as we are walk towards our Santiagos, so long as we walk with life, so long as we are trying to honor the inner light within each of us. Without light, life cannot exist, and life cannot exist without shadow. But that’s ok. Because at the end of the day, we are walking towards the sun, towards Santiago, and our shadow is now behind us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met a French girl named Pauline while wandering around Terradillo de Templarios. She was walking to the next town, so I decided to accompany her until the edge of Terradillo. She&amp;rsquo;s been walking for over 1000 kilometers, all the way from Paris. Said she was feeling lost, but was ok with it. She wasn’t searching for anything, she simply enjoyed walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While waiting for the shop to open, an older South Korean woman said I looked like a kind person. That made my day. She did also. I learned she was walking alone. She said the Camino had given her peace and a more full heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve just had the most interesting dinner with an elderly woman named Elizabeth. She&amp;rsquo;s 72 years old, walking alone, German. Her eyes glimmered with maternal gentleness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was her and I at a small dining table in the restaurant. I started talking to her but soon realized she did not understand a single word. She spoke back in German, and I was just as confused as she. The curve of a wry smile formed on each of our faces as we humored the situation. She continued talking to me in German, and I continued responding in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the wine came. Glass after glass, drink after drink, the wine flowed like a river. And pretty soon, we were bent over in laughter, pointing at nothings and waving our arms and legs in strange, unintelligible ways. I got drunk with an elderly 72-year-old German lady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She showed me some pictures of her family, and I showed her mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ah, beautiful! Beautiful!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a delightfully nonsensical and ridiculous time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-26-2017-day-20&#34;&gt;September 26, 2017 - Day 20&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you see the magic if you don&amp;rsquo; t believe in it?
It’s all around, in the trees, the grass, the flowers, the birdsong.
I see it in the sun, I taste it in the wind, I feel it with my smile.
This moment, this is it. An ocean of possibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into San! We haven’t seen each other since Day 1. Crazy. He looks great, and he’s found other friends – Karla, Dori, and Leo. Karla and Dori are from Croatia while Leo is from Czechia. They invited me to have dinner with them. Of course, I gladly accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, we went to watch the sunset. I was annoyed by Karla because she was constantly on her phone, talking and blabbering about essentially nothing. I decided to go to the other side of the park to watch it by myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I miss Marieke and her present presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pauline. She’s here! In my room! She and her French friend, Morgan, are going to start walking tomorrow at 4:30am. They want to see some shooting stars and have invited me to tag along. I was initially hesitant but have agreed to go. Not sure what I&amp;rsquo;ve dragged myself into, but it should be good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/journal1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>9: An Ode to the Road</title>
        <link>/posts/ode/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/ode/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Each and every day I wake and walk with the sun.&lt;br&gt;
It starts low, climbing over hillsides, rising slowly.&lt;br&gt;
It finds its temporary place amid the sky&lt;br&gt;
and begins to color the Meseta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Front and center a shadow grows.&lt;br&gt;
It looks at me with indifference – a mirror of my darker side.&lt;br&gt;
Fear, insecurity, doubt,&lt;br&gt;
The manifestation of my inner demons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every day, I wake and walk and confront them.&lt;br&gt;
If I fight and struggle, I hurt and suffer.&lt;br&gt;
If I push them away, I push myself away.&lt;br&gt;
I cannot hide, I cannot run,&lt;br&gt;
I can only bear witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salvation lies within absence. &lt;br&gt;
But do I do it? Do I dare eclipse the sun?&lt;br&gt;
To turn from the shadows is to turn from truth.&lt;br&gt;
I would be swallowed whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My shadow is here,&lt;br&gt;
my shadow is me.&lt;br&gt;
So long as I walk the Way,&lt;br&gt;
it will keep me company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t be scared&lt;br&gt;
I mustn&amp;rsquo;t be afraid.&lt;br&gt;
I must continue on and on and on,&lt;br&gt;
moving toward the falling sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each and every day, I wake and walk towards Santiago.&lt;br&gt;
The closer I get, the lighter I feel.&lt;br&gt;
The sun hangs low, peering over hillsides, descending slowly.&lt;br&gt;
Color fades from the Meseta, and my shadow is behind me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Westward lies Santiago, and I look.&lt;br&gt;
The sun has set, the dark has settled.&lt;br&gt;
A fire begins to grow deep inside.&lt;br&gt;
It lights the valley and shows me the Way.&lt;br&gt;
I wake and walk toward the Light,&lt;br&gt;
closer and closer to Santiago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/ode.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>8: Gone</title>
        <link>/posts/gone/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/gone/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve sunken into the depths of an all-too-familiar melancholy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is gone. I am alone. My emotions swing to the erratic cadence of an unforgiving metronome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;
I’m fine. Tick. &lt;br&gt;
I’m fine. Tick. &lt;br&gt;
I’m not. Tick. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I miss the jade of her eyes, those luminescent opals I so often lose myself in. The ease of her smile, always able to bring about my own. The way she plucked those juicy blackberries from their thorny brambles, always a tad out of reach, the hem of her shirt lifting ever so slightly in the process, revealing the contours of a titillating landscape I secretly wished to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I miss her laugh, her presence, the way she made me feel: Whole. Complete. Loved. I miss my Camino soulmate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Absence: the paradoxical presence of nothingness. A palpable emptiness. A space defined by its non-existence. A torturous conundrum that slowly gnaws away the seams of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A universe without incandescence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepan has decided to stay another night in Burgos. Strange. He’s not taking the leave well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, on the other hand, have to go. I have to keep walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sky reflects my mood – gray, somber, displaced. I walk through a park between a row of trees. A runner waves at me and says, “Buen Camino!” I force a smile and wave back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m lost – the hostel we stayed at was located somewhere deep within the city, far from the familiar path of the Camino. I need to find a yellow arrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, Google Maps leads me back on track. I spot a yellow arrow on a blue signpost pointing towards a stone bridge. A group of Spanish schoolchildren are crossing. I follow. They turn and smile at me. &amp;ldquo;Un peregrino!&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; This time an unforced grin wiggles its way to my lips. What I would do to be a child right now: they are experts at being present and letting go of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past 15 days I have walked with another. Now she’s gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remnant of what was, a reminder of what isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the western edge of Burgos, I feel the presence of someone following me. I turn back and spot an older man trailing me not far behind. Some minutes later he appears at my shoulder, decelerates, and matches my pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ah, hello. You are young.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No I’m Phil.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He doesn’t get the joke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let me mope alone &amp;ndash; we walk together for the next 2 hours. He&amp;rsquo;s a Korean Catholic priest on sabbatical. We proceed to talk about religion, the Camino, life. It&amp;rsquo;s refreshing to hear another voice, to have a moment of mental relief. Somehow he notices the concern I&amp;rsquo;m carrying and asks why I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m not sure anymore. I guess I was looking for a purpose, but I don&amp;rsquo;t even know if I believe in such a thing. But I feel like I have been going through life on a path that is not my own. Also, my friend just left. We had been walking together for the past 2 weeks, and now she’s gone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That must be hard&amp;hellip; let me ask you something: What are the most important things in your life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&amp;hellip;I&amp;hellip; I don’t know.” I felt ashamed for not knowing, but he reassured me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t worry. Most people have answers right away. But they haven’t thought about why; Why are those things important? It&amp;rsquo;s ok not to know.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What makes you excited and happy?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well… right now, walking. And I&amp;rsquo;m enjoying my conversation with you. I like to learn. I like to travel and meet people. Anything that makes me feel alive.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ok, I see where you’re going with this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s ok not to know. You don’t have to know where you’re going, you just need to keep going. And as long as you ask Why, you will go where you need to be. You might be searching for a clear answer, but it’s ok if you don’t find one by the end of your journey. Just keep asking Why, and be open to whatever comes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As a child, I had the calling to become a priest. But I decided to go to university to study architecture instead. I designed buildings for almost 15 years. I thought it was what I wanted. But something inside me told me it wasn’t. That was my heart speaking. It was still saying I had to become a priest. So I listened, and here I am! Ha ha.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;But I don’t have a calling.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But you do. Callings! You just need to listen. Listen to your heart.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go on like this for awhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Can we take a picture together?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He took out his phone and snaps a selfie of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I will always remember you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He laughs, quickens his pace, and walks off into the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never saw him again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 34 kilometers I arrive in Hontanas. I check myself in, unpack, shower, and cook a light dinner. I wander around town for a bit, then go inside the church and sit in silence. I thought the presence of God would help me fill the void, but it didn’t. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t help non-believers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I leave and clamber up a narrow flight of stairs behind the albergue. At the top is a swing-set and what looks like an abandoned bar. I continue upward toward the top of the hill until the people below are nothing more than ants. Barren hilltops and stretched clouds pressed against the distance. The sun is beginning its daily descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why do I feel this way? I thought I had let her go. I thought I had accepted what was. Yesterday I was fine, today I&amp;rsquo;m not. What happened? Is this what it feels like to let go of something, someone you love? Do I though? Do I really love her?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began to vocalize my thoughts by talking to the sky, as if someone was listening to my grievances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I accept it. Yes, I miss her. Maybe I do love her. I don’t know. What is love anyways? It’s so cliche. Boy meets girl in Spain. Falls in love. She flies away. and he lies to himself, tells himself he’s ok. He’s not. I miss her.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A weight was lifting as I shouted. I laugh and imagine M at my side, laughing with me, telling me how crazy of a person I am for talking to myself, shouting at nothing but the sun and clouds. But I knew she would understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A latch releases. Gratitude, clarity, stillness, tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sky is poppy red, M’s favorite flower and color, a deep and radiant crimson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey has only just begun. Moving forward is all there&amp;rsquo;s left to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/gone.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>7: Goodbye</title>
        <link>/posts/goodbye/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/goodbye/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Day 15. We’re sitting amid a small cluster of dining tables in the main plaza of Burgos, sipping on wine and eating tapas. The patrons and pilgrims look happy, the cathedral towers above us. I look up and wonder, is there such a thing as a good goodbye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marieke looks content and tells her squirrel joke again. I try to listen, but my attention has been seized by the fact that she is leaving tonight. I take a sip of wine, and we continue talking. Stepan – a pilgrim from Czech we had met some days ago – is with us. He reminds me of a winter wolf. His hair is white like snow with hints of dark gray. He’s observant and quiet. Does Marieke notice the way he looks at her? Or how I do too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepan and I book a hostel. We want one night to ourselves and away from the congested albergues of the Camino. We drop our things off and go to dinner at our favorite restaurant &amp;ndash; the one with the Falafel &amp;ndash; with Marieke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stepan goes to the bathroom, and I give M the bus note I had written for her earlier that day. We replay every scene and memory of the days that have passed. They seem so long ago. She rests her head on my shoulder and we sit in silence, wishing for the coming of tomorrow to cease its advance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly Marieke spots our tall Texan, Stefan, walking across the middle of the plaza. And at his sides are Matilde and Franca!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sprint toward the lovable Germans, screaming their names in unison. I hurl myself onto Franca and give her the biggest hug of my life, nearly knocking over an elderly couple in the process. Their timing could be no more perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9pm. We’re in the bus station. Marieke is leaving soon. I have her listen to “Soul Meets Body” by Death Cab for Cutie. Stepan is standing a few meters away from us, searching for the bus, as if he were the one leaving. Maybe he’s giving Marieke and I some space. Earlier, he had said that he didn&amp;rsquo;t do goodbyes well. Does anyone?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus finally arrives. Marieke and I embrace, and time bends itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To our sentimental whims. To our refusal to let go of the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are desparately refusing a future in which &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; will be nothing more than a memory, a firing of indifferent, constantly reforming neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It bends because we are fighting for the ineffable, for something so palpably insatiable, for what I have felt for the first time in my life: love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a love that is expansive, all-encompassing, enrapturing. It digs deeper than traditional notions of romanticism, flies higher than the devout&amp;rsquo;s devotion to God, questions everything I thought I had understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is bending because we will not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus parks. People are hailed over. We let go. She boards. I look at her one last time. She looks back. The hint of a smile creeps over her lips like a foreign facade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engine comes to life, and the bus is wheeled into the dim tunnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time reclaims its throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She&amp;rsquo;s gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By some convergence of chance and choice, Marieke and I met and walked together on the Camino for two weeks. Those weeks were some of the best in my life. Her energy and enthusiasm for life was unmatched. Every blackberry she ate, every sip of coffee she had, every conversation we held was something to be cherished. She taught me that only by giving oneself up to life could life be fully lived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you’re sad, feel sad. Happy, feel happy. Whatever it is, don’t push it away.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Having emotions just means you’re alive!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To her life was a privilege, not a birthright, and she embraced it with every ounce of her being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One week in, she said I had become her best friend. Now, I won’t lie. When she said this, I started imagining all kinds of romantic fantasies and happy endings between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hey children, your ol’ Gramps met this lovely lady 35 years ago while walking across Spain! It was destiny!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, cool story bro, but I met my love on the Camino.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet what we had was so much deeper than that. To her, my insecurities, fears, and struggles were valid parts of me. And yet, in comparison to my strengths as a human, they were wholly insignificant. She appreciated, awed at, and encouraged my child-like curiosity, the way I saw the world, and the purity of being she believed me to possess. “You have something special to give to the world.” She was relentless in her attempts of making me believe in myself. I did. I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a natural human impulse to try and define our experiences and relationships by the predefined narratives we&amp;rsquo;ve accumulated over the course of our lifetime. Sometimes though, these boxes are too narrow. They&amp;rsquo;re limited by what we&amp;rsquo;ve seen and been exposed to in the past. They fail to capture or miss entirely the nuances and brevity of new and profound experiences. Some things are best left undefined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/goodbye.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>6: Sunsets and Soulmates</title>
        <link>/posts/suns-souls/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/suns-souls/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Phil! I have a genius idea. You’re really going to like it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the 12th day. Marieke, Stepan and I go to the top of a hill to catch the sunset. We sift through an amber field of grass and wheat and settle ourselves in a small circular clearing. The sky is cloudless, a cool breeze is present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talk for awhile, about what I cant&amp;rsquo;t remember, but I feel wonderfully content. When the sun begins its descent into the edge of the horizon, we are overcome by the growing silence of the landscape. With each passing minute, the birds chirped louder and louder, almost as if they were calling to their friends, “Come! The miracle is happening again!” Then their voices disappeared. Layer by layer, the orange and pinkish hues faded into the dark absolute of space and night while the stars took their place against the blackened sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hey Marieke, can I share something with you?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrap my arm around her and pull her close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My body heat.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She presses her body closer to mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You are so incredibly lame.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marieke is always able to find the joy in every moment. Each and every time we came across a blackberry bush, she would always stop to eat a few. With eyes closed and a perked body, each bite was a delectable gift from the Camino. With coffee or tortillas, she would always exclaim, “This is the best coffee/tortilla I’ve ever tasted!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask her what the secret is to enjoying life, and she laughs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh it’s so simple, Phil.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Is it though?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It is not something you can do with the mind, it is something you must feel with your heart.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Well that&amp;rsquo;s not helpful,&amp;rdquo; I jab. &amp;ldquo;What if my heart doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel anything?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t be silly. Just listen to it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moments later, Marieke tells us her story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 years ago, she had nearly committed suicide. She was part of a rigorous doctorate program for engineering. She hated it, she didn&amp;rsquo;t belong. It just wasn’t for her, yet she desperately tried to claw her way through. To cope with the stress, she stopped eating for days at a time – it got her mind off the engineering. After months of this, her body could no longer handle the starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the hospital, she told her family that she was going to walk the Camino (this would be her first of three; we met on her third). Everyone said she was crazy to even think of such an idea in her current physical and mental state. But she ignored them and flew to Spain. A greater force was beckoning: the need to save herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each passing day and every fallen footstep, she grew emotionally, physically, and mentally stronger. Lightness, joy, and gratitude began to inhabit her soul. Food tasted good again, indescribably good, so much so that she would often be brought to tears while eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then understood why every tortilla, coffee, and blackberry was the best thing in the world to her: life and its constitutes had become an indispensable gift. The best days were the ones in which she was alive and well enough to savor it. I wondered, Does it take such a close encounter to death to acknowledge the beauty of what is right before us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When she reached Santiago, she fell to her knees and cried. She had proven her family wrong. She had made it. And she had found a reason to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After she finishes telling us her story, I read her &amp;ldquo;The Journey&amp;rdquo; by Mary Oliver:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day you finally knew&lt;br&gt;
what you had to do, and began,&lt;br&gt;
though the voices around you&lt;br&gt;
kept shouting&lt;br&gt;
their bad advice–&lt;br&gt;
though the whole house&lt;br&gt;
began to tremble&lt;br&gt;
and you felt the old tug&lt;br&gt;
at your ankles.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Mend my life!&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;
each voice cried.&lt;br&gt;
But you didn&amp;rsquo;t stop.&lt;br&gt;
You knew what you had to do,&lt;br&gt;
though the wind pried&lt;br&gt;
with its stiff fingers&lt;br&gt;
at the very foundations,&lt;br&gt;
though their melancholy&lt;br&gt;
was terrible.&lt;br&gt;
It was already late&lt;br&gt;
enough, and a wild night,&lt;br&gt;
and the road full of fallen&lt;br&gt;
branches and stones.&lt;br&gt;
But little by little,&lt;br&gt;
as you left their voices behind,&lt;br&gt;
the stars began to burn&lt;br&gt;
through the sheets of clouds,&lt;br&gt;
and there was a new voice&lt;br&gt;
which you slowly&lt;br&gt;
recognized as your own,&lt;br&gt;
that kept you company&lt;br&gt;
as you strode deeper and deeper&lt;br&gt;
into the world,&lt;br&gt;
determined to do&lt;br&gt;
the only thing you could do&amp;ndash;&lt;br&gt;
determined to save&lt;br&gt;
the only life you could save.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No words could express the gratitude I felt at that moment. I was thankful that she was alive and with us in a cold field somewhere in Spain. Stepan eventually caved and accepted our invitation to share body heat under the cool night sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why did the universe bring us all together?” I ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don&amp;rsquo;t know, but I believe that everything happens for a reason,&amp;rdquo; said Marieke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think, &amp;ldquo;What if we&amp;rsquo;re the ones who make those reasons?&amp;rdquo; then let the thought go. In that moment, it just didn&amp;rsquo;t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/roses.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>5: The Cusp of Time and Infinity</title>
        <link>/posts/cusp/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/cusp/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the morning we walk to Pamplona, our first city. I run into Maria and chat with her for a brief moment before running off with the girls to get breakfast. I didn’t know it then, but that would be my final conversation with her. One thing the Camino teaches you, by nature of necessity, is how to let go. People, places, your past. The present demands it be so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stop at a small bakery near the entrance of the city. The owners are friendly, the chocolate and pastries delectable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/cusp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first day I distance myself from the group. At our usual lunch time, I decide to continue walking. I felt the need to recenter myself, to have some alone time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tell the girls and they understand – they even encourage it – and I walk on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The landscape opens, and I can see for miles on end in every direction. Small farms and grainy fields, naked mountains and green hilltops populating the horizon. As I walk into the vastness, I feel a growing sense of calm, a clarity of mind, and a strengthening of body and soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/cusp1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reach Zariquiegui much sooner than expected. Marieke arrives shortly after as do Matilde and Franca, and we check into a small albergue attached to a small bar. We reconvene outside and chat over drinks. I&amp;rsquo;m drinking red wine, Marieke has her milk, Franca and Matilde their beers. Afterwards we separate again and explore the town on our own. I walk up a small hill overlooking Zariquiegui, write, and meditate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my way back down, I catch sight of Marieke sitting on a curb listening to music. I go over and ask if I can join. She tells me the music she listens to is unusual and “not fit for [my] American ears,&amp;rdquo; but she eventually concedes her right earbud. The melodies are soothing and enjoyable, but I don&amp;rsquo;t understand a single word – it was all in French.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, the girls and I go up a modest hill at the edge of town and lay down in the grass for awhile, gazing at stars, telling stupid jokes, enjoying our newfound friendships. In the distance, tiny orbs of light give shape to the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t want the moment to end. We were all high on life, strangers united by foreignness, drinking from the cusp of time and infinity, somewhere in the depths of a beautiful and wonderfully dark universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/cusp2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>4: Möge die Straße</title>
        <link>/posts/strasse/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/strasse/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;p&gt;Another gray and rainy day. We sleep in and start walking at 8am. After the deep and enlightening conversations of yesterday, we decide to walk in solitude –– together, but left to the vicinity of our inner worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feelings throughout the morning are in contrast with the highs of the previous; I was in a blue, melancholic state of mind. Thoughts of the future, about something out of reach. What if I return unchanged? What if the Camino turns out to be a waste of time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m annoyed at myself for having these thoughts, though I don’t push them away. I try to listen and see them as they are – thoughts with no actual bearing on reality, despite how real they feel in the moment. Acknowledged, their presence begins to simply fade, and I am able to resume my walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 2 hours of trekking, we stop at a small cafe and break our vow of silence. And lucky us! The solitude has given us time to generate new and creative insights, while the distance fueled a burning desire for each other&amp;rsquo;s company. It was like we were seeing old friends again after years of prolonged distance, and we enjoyed each minute as if they were our last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/strasse1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continue our walk, though without much of the silence. I walk with Matilde this time while Franca and Marieke are a few paces ahead of us. Something seems to be on Matilde’s mind, so I inquire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matilde had just graduated from high school and was taking the year off before planning to apply for university. This was her first time being away from home. At the bus station in Bayonne, right before she and Franca had met me, she reported having a mental breakdown, understandably so. Not only was she adjusting to the fact that she was far from home, she was also about to walk across a completely unknown, unfamiliar country. But she understood that what she was experiencing was just a small part of growing up. She knew she would be fine, especially in good company. I admired her courageous and optimistic spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talk about a variety of topics: destiny, fate, family, love, and of course, books. I&amp;rsquo;m thrilled to discover that Matilde is also a voracious bibliophile. Both of us are baffled to learn that the wonderful novel, Cloud Atlas, is a shared favorite. Most people have heard of and seen the movie, but it was much less likely that they have heard of or read the book. The language is lucid but dense. What were the odds of meeting someone on the Camino who had actually read the book? Was there a reason behind the sudden entwinement of our universes, like that of the six protagonists of Cloud Atlas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before meeting, Matilde had thought my name was Timothy: “You just looked like a Timothy, so Franca and I decided to call you Timothy.” I flipped out and told her my Dad&amp;rsquo;s name was Timothy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could have dismissed these moments as a series of mere coincidences. But we didn&amp;rsquo;t. We don&amp;rsquo;t. Where&amp;rsquo;s the fun in that? We, as humans, have the power to write our own narratives through the meaning we give to our shared experiences. We are both the pen and the paper on which they are writen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Etched in the script of the starry cosmos was the convergence of two seemingly disparate universes, that of Matilde and Phil, on the 10th day of a gray and rainy September in the year of 2017 on the Camino de Santiago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We end our walk at a quiet donation-based albergue some few kilometers from the city of Pamplona. The albergue has a calm and inviting atmosphere. On the walls are colorful plates and pictures, paintings of pilgrims, various cultural articles. My favorite piece is a poster with the word love transcribed in multiple languages, likely written by past pilgrims who had also found refuge in this albergue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After unpacking and cleaning myself up, I go downstairs and into the kitchen and meet a pilgrim named Maria. She&amp;rsquo;s from Oregon and had recently retired from working as a speech therapist and professor. To celebrate she decided to walk the Camino. We start talking and I tell her I&amp;rsquo;m searching for direction, that I feel quite lost and unsure of what I want in life. She listens attentively and and allows me to vent my thoughts for at least an hour. When I finish, she smiles and reassures me the way a loving mother does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Don’t worry. You’ll figure it out as you go. Everyone walks their own path. You need to be practical, yes, but you also need to listen to your own heart. That’s why you’re here now. Just keep walking and listen to what the Camino tells you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the evening, the girls and I go inside the church behind our albergue and ring the infamous bell at the top of its tower. It is the only bell allowed to be rung by pilgrims on the Camino. Afterwards we go downstairs, and I notice a small shrine covered with green sticky notes surrounding an effigy of Jesus. On them are the writings of many past pilgrims, mostly notes of gratitude. Matilde, Franca, Marieke, and I add our own to the collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later that night, we share a dinner with the others – more pasta, salad, wine. Once we finish, we go into the church again for a short reflection lead by the nuns who help maintain the albergue. We sit in a small circle, and each of us shares who we are and, voluntarily, why we are walking the Camino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a man walking with his young son, James, the young woman to my left is searching for a new source of meaning, and Maria is walking in celebration of her long and rich life. I consider the question and give my own answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end the night, Matilde and Franca are asked to sing a song. They decide to sing an Irish blessing song, Möge die Straße, in German. It was something they sang at the end of every school year before departing into the bliss of their summer vacations. The setting was perfect. We had no essence of what adventures, trials, and lessons lay ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;möge-die-straße&#34;&gt;Möge die Straße&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May the road rise to meet you&lt;br&gt;
May the wind be always at your back&lt;br&gt;
May the sun shine warm upon your face&lt;br&gt;
The rains fall soft upon your fields&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And until we meet again, until we meet again&lt;br&gt;
May God hold you in the palm of his hand&lt;br&gt;
And until we meet again, until we meet again&lt;br&gt;
May God hold you in the palm of his hand&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May the sun make your days bright&lt;br&gt;
May the stars illuminate your nights&lt;br&gt;
May the flowers bloom along your path&lt;br&gt;
Your house stand firm against the storm&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And until we meet again, until we meet again&lt;br&gt;
May God hold you in the palm of his hand&lt;br&gt;
And until we meet again, until we meet again&lt;br&gt;
May God hold you in the palm of his hand&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/strasse2.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>3: Tea</title>
        <link>/posts/tea/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/tea/</guid>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through the window I see &lt;br&gt;
Sun-bathed flowers and untouched rock,&lt;br&gt;
Blades of grass and untrodden walks,&lt;br&gt;
Endless possibility.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask of you Time&lt;br&gt;
To yield your determined hand&lt;br&gt;
So I may dance&lt;br&gt;
Forever with Infinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run into Matilde and Franca while departing from Roncesvalles. They&amp;rsquo;re headed in the opposite direction, back toward the albergue, when they call out to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Phiiiiilll! Heeeey we’re gonna make some tea! Would you like to join us?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words of a wise hospitalero echo in my mind: The Camino will give you everything you need. Surrender to the Way. Be open to what comes your way, he said. In other words, say yes to life unless you have a good reason not to &amp;ndash; there never is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go back inside and attempt to make the tea. Matilde and Franca fiddle with the stove while I watch and provide moral support. Unfortunately the stove is beyond the abilities of my fellow Germans, so I give the task a go myself. I fail miserably. Having failed, I go to find Matilde and Franca and discover them chatting with a young Belgian near the vending machines in the adjacent kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I introduce myself and join the conversation. The Belgian&amp;rsquo;s name is Marieke. She seemed excited about the fact that we were young and spoke fluent English, unlike many of the other pilgrims here. Some minutes later, Franca and Matilde go back into the kitchen, leaving Marieke and I to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marieke was in her 2nd year of medical school. She&amp;rsquo;s on the Camino seeking balance, answers. It&amp;rsquo;s her 3rd one, though she has never walked its entire length. Her acute sense of self-awareness, her clear display of buoyancy, and her attentive hazel eyes catch me off guard. I am mesmerized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day is gray and rainy, a complete contrast to the sun-painted stroll of the prior. We decide it&amp;rsquo;s best to walk together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walk with Marieke while Matilde and Franca trot together a few meters ahead of us. Marieke is wearing a clear, plastic trashbag she claims is a poncho. &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s not a poncho, that&amp;rsquo;s a trash bag!&amp;rdquo; - it takes her awhile to warm up to my humor. Once we&amp;rsquo;re beyond the formalities, Marieke and I begin to talk about every imaginable topic a human-being like me loves: psychology, purpose, meaning, meditation, freewill, learning, being. Eventually we exchange the intellectual brevity for emotional depth: we talk about pain and love, relationships and ourselves, the finitude of our time in this world. We get vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was growing attracted to her and tried to brush it off because I didn’t want to feel this way – &amp;ldquo;this is not why I&amp;rsquo;m here,&amp;rdquo; I remind myself. But love and attraction don&amp;rsquo;t quite adhere to our more sensible selves, and I am reminded to surrender to the Way. &amp;ldquo;The Camino will give you everything you need,&amp;rdquo; echoed the Hospilatero. But was this something I needed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we walk on, I grow increasingly aware of the beauty surrounding us: the colors and smells, the rhythm of my footsteps, the movements of nature. My senses are heightened, and I feel incredibly alive. Marieke too is clearly captivated –– by the droplets of water hanging from the leaves, by the dewy smell of the moist air, by the simple joy of freedom. And before we&amp;rsquo;re aware of it, we arrive in Zubiri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single shower in our albergue is occupied. Matilde and Marieke inform me that there&amp;rsquo;s a shared shower space downstairs in the other building. I go, believing that it would be unoccupied by other pilgrims since we had arrived later in the day. As I make my way toward the other building, I see another young pilgrim walking towards it too, equipped with clean clothes and a small bottle of shampoo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oh boy. I’m going to have to shower with another dude. Wait, there must be stalls. Yeah, it’s all good.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no stalls. Only a long aisle with a single curtain hiding a row of shower-heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go inside. He acknowledges me with a quick head-nod, and I nod back. We step into the aisle. I turn my back to him and began to take off my clothes; he does the same, I think. I&amp;rsquo;ve claimed one corner while he the other. And then we start showering, no more than six meters apart. I take my time, hoping that he will finish before me. He must’ve had the same thought, because we are both standing there for several minutes, showering together in silence, serenaded by the clashing of water against our exposed skin. Finally, I make the first move and finish my shower. He continues. I dry myself off, put my clothes on, and scurry away from the building. I report my experience to the girls, and they&amp;rsquo;re hysterical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see him again later, and we give each other a quick nod of acknowledgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A man on the Camino told me he was walking because he wanted to find peace: peace with himself. Peace with nature. Peace with God.” – Marieke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girls and I go to get a drink at the local bar. There we run into Stefan, the tall, lanky, 18-year-old Texan. He&amp;rsquo;s been drinking since 2pm and is clearly inebriated. We eat pizza - Spanish pizza! - and banter on about our respective home countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marieke leaves early to catch some alone time, and I go and do the same. Back in the albergue, I reflect on the day and write in my journal. Later, I find Marieke sitting in the corner of the kitchen, perhaps also writing about her day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talk to a woman in her 60&amp;rsquo;s from the States. We exchange some stories, she about her career and children, I about my recent adventures and worries for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She reassured me, “It&amp;rsquo;ll work itself out, so don’t worry so much. Hell, I’m still learning how how not to.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never grow tired of telling my stories to different people. Each retelling refined or redefined the meaning I derive from my experiences. I thank the woman for listening and sharing her stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franca and Matilde return from the bar, and we join Marieke in the corner of the kitchen. Later we enjoy a community dinner with the other pilgrims, and when the wine has settled in our bodies, we retreat to our room and dream of the coming day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/tea.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>2: First Ascent</title>
        <link>/posts/firstascent/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/firstascent/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke to the sound of creaking bunk beds, rustling backpacks, and hushed chatter. 5:30 a.m. &lt;em&gt;Time to go.&lt;/em&gt; I put my boots on, packed my sleeping bag, and went downstairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small talk of good weather and stellar walking conditions and free bread as stiff as stones. I devour as much of it as my mouth can muster and head out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first day was supposed to be arduous: 27 kilometers from Saint-Jean to Roncesvalles, with a gradual gain of 1400 meters in elevation. It was dark, cold, and misty out. Regardless, I equip myself with a smile, shoulder my rucksack, and begin putting one foot in front of the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of the morning I walk along a narrow road populated by small farms and modest homes. A constant stream of white vans drives by, presumably transporting those who are daunted by the unavoidable ascent over the Pyrenees, or those who are physically incapable. The air stinks of manure and wheat, though I felt invigorated by a sense of new beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 5-6 kilometers of walking in the twilight, I reach the base of the Pyrenees. I allow myself a short break, then began the ascent. As I climb higher into the sky, the sun is rising to fulfill its daily task. Clumps of green become discernible blades of grass, darkness turns to shadow, cowbells and birdsong fill the air. The landscape is awakening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sheer variety of walkers amazes me. Young and old; American and Canadian, English and Irish; German, Hungarian, Italian, Polish; Korean, Japanese… the list is endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to discern those who are on vacation from those who are in search of something greater. The vacationers often walked in couples or groups. Their conversations were light, suffering was a force to be avoided, they lacked a spiritual connection to the Camino. Conversely, the seekers usually walked alone. They connected with other soloists and seekers, their suffering was meaningful, the Camino had called to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, these are only superficial observations. A person could be walking for deeply personal reasons, but had decided to go with others because they are simply terrified of walking alone. And certainly there&amp;rsquo;s the spiritual bunch who act like hound dogs on a life-or-death mission; they&amp;rsquo;re the ones who often lose sight of the very thing they&amp;rsquo;re seeking - it was often right under their noses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrive at Refuge Orisson two hours later, an albergue about 8 kilometers west of Saint-Jean. I take a break and buy myself another round of breakfast – espresso with a Spanish tortilla. The mountainous air feels cool and refreshing, the views from the terrace are stunning. I fill my lungs and exhale slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/orr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on the road, I am greeted by a cheery social worker from South Korea named San. He doesn’t speak much English, but when he does, it&amp;rsquo;s usually about someting positive, and he always laughs at my jokes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We meet another South Korean named Jackie moments later. She worked in hospitality for a year before deciding that she was dissatisfied with her life. She&amp;rsquo;s a seeker, and unlike San, her English is fluent. She understands my jokes but doesn’t laugh at them the way San does. Regardless, we welcome her company and walk together for the next two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solitude exists only in stolen moments during the early stages of the Camino. San and Jackie need a break, so I continue on without them, knowing that we will reconnect in Roncesvalles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A continual stream of other pilgrims takes their place. It&amp;rsquo;s overwhelming at times, all the &amp;lsquo;Buen Caminos!&amp;rsquo; and fleeting conversations. I appreciated their earnest attempts to connect, but often I wanted to be alone with the scenary. That was something I was still trying to learn: how to accept and be open to the unexpected company of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrive at Roncesvalles early in the afternoon. It’s a small town with two restaurant-bars, a hotel, and a gothic monastery that accommodates 200 or so pilgrims. After checking in, I idle in the courtyard, call my parents, and write in my journal. Later, Jackie and I grab a drink at the local bar to celebrate our first full day of walking. Afterwards we go to the nearby restaurant for dinner with some of the other pilgrims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard pilgrim meal consists of an appetizer, the main dish, and dessert, of which was always accompanied by a bottle of red wine. Always. By the end of the night our tongues were loose, and we began exchanging stories of who we were, where we came from, and why we were walking the Camino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spanish couple at our table had recently returned to Spain after having lived in London for several years, stating that life in the city was too complicated. They preferred the simple lifestyle of Spain, and they were walking the Camino to celebrate their homecoming. Another man from Italy shares that he has been walking the Camino every year for the past five years. He liked the perspective he gained and the people he met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Everyone has a story to share on the Camino. I come here to learn and listen,” he said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, I retreat to my bunk bed and journal about the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking in unknown territory nourished me. I felt alive and powerful, small and humbled beneath the Spanish skies. Perhaps I was here to write the rest of my own story; to rediscover and map the terrain of my own heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I check the contents of my rucksack again. Three outfits and two pairs of socks. A sleeping bag and a down jacket. Phone charger, toiletries, another set of shoes in addition to my boots. Just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emergency medical supplies for three days. The KIND bars have been shared and devoured; my 1-liter nalgene bottle is filled to the brim. My California license plate––the only item of sentimental value. A journal and my writing tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take a deep breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let it go, slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re two sides of the same coin, and I am standing on the precipice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/road.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>1: Beginnings</title>
        <link>/posts/beginnings/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/beginnings/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Camino de Santiago is a network of pilgrimage routes that ultimately converge on the city of Santiago de Compostela in Northwestern Spain, where the great Saint James is rumored to be buried.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most popular route is the Camino Frances. It begins at Saint-Jean-Pied-de-Port in Southern France, a small city located north of the Pyrenees, and totals about 500 miles across Spain to the city of Santiago de Compostela. Many walk the Camino for spiritual and religious reasons; I walked in search of myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first challenge of the Camino is actually getting on the Camino. Since my starting point was Saint-Jean, I needed to take a flight from Charles de Gaulle Airport to Biarritz –– a small city in Southwestern France –– and from Biarritz a bus to the nearby city of Bayonne, and from Bayonne another bus to Saint-Jean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made my first two friends while waiting in line to board the plane in Charles de Gaulle airport. There was a tap on my shoulder, and I turned around to meet Jim and Kathy, a genial, retired couple from Truckee, California. They believed that life was too short to be lived at the wayside. Retirement and old age should enable one’s life, they said, not inhibit it. So they decided to walk the Camino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we were in Biarritz, we had to catch a bus to Bayonne. Jim and Kathy said it would cost one euro to board. Unfortunately, I didn’t have any euros yet, and a currency exchange was nowhere to be found. I returned to the bus stop, and Jim noticed my concerned expression. I told him I had no euros. He laughed in response and handed me one. I was surprised by his casual generosity and thanked him. I looked at Jim and Kathy and smiled. Their sharp blue eyes radiated with youth and sincerity. It seemed as if the Camino was conspiring to make the journey possible, as if I were integral to the writing of some larger story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met my second pair of friends, Franca and Matilde, the dynamic 18-year-old German duo, while waiting in Bayonne. It began with a simple request:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hallo! Do you mind watching our stuff while we use the toilet?” Matilde asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah! Of course,” I replied. But toilet? Was this some form of European vernacular for bathroom? As it turns out, it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus finally arrived and we were on our way to Saint-Jean. I sat in the back of the bus where I had a panoramic view of the Pyrenees mountains. The sun-bathed ridges pierced the clear blue skies, reminding me of my many hikes in the White Mountains of New Hampshire. The shadows of leaves formed, disappeared, and reemerged in rapid oscillations on my body as we drove through the valley, a simple play of light that delighted my eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I directed my attention back into the bus and took notice of the numerous people before me. Matilde and Franca were sitting near the front next to a tall, lanky Texan named Stefan. I then turned my gaze toward Jim and Cathy. Jim was resisting Cathy’s attempts to straddle him. He looked somewhat embarrassed, but I knew he was reveling in the moment. Their eyes spoke of a timeless love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an hour or so we arrived in Saint-Jean-Pied-de-Port, the official starting point of the Camino Frances. In the near distance stood the Pyrenees, the grand guardians of the city, and on the other side rested Spain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the length of the Camino, there are hundreds of yellow arrows marked on walls, tree stumps, and signposts. Their sole purpose is to lead the pilgrim toward Santiago de Compostela, the end destination of the Camino. So long as you followed the arrow, you were presumably going the right way. To trust the arrow is to make a connection with all of the past pilgrims who had already embarked on the journey. It is the first leap of faith on the Camino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon arriving in Saint-Jean, my first task was to obtain a credencial. It was required to stay in the albergues –– the pilgrim hostels –– and, if you cared for it, for the certificate of completion in Santiago. I followed a trail of yellow arrows into Saint-Jean, found the Pilgrim’s Office, and received my first stamp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had booked an albergue in advance, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t open yet, so I went to explore Saint-Jean. The cobblestone roads were furnished by a myriad of markets, sandwich shops, charcuteries, restaurants and kiosks. Plastered on their fronts was the notorious scallop shell of the Camino. The shell represents the idea that all paths eventually lead to Santiago. This struck me as a rich metaphor for life: wherever we are going, whatever path we are on, we will always be lead to Truth, God, oneself. Maybe there is no wrong path in life, so long as we kept walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The albergue opened at 4 p.m. Inside, the other pilgrims and I were greeted by a man who could have been characterized as the Yoda of the Camino. He was our hospitalero, the person in charge of running the albergue. Before checking us in, he sat us down and told us a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When you wake up tomorrow,” he began, “and you want to make yourself a cup of coffee, please make sure to give the machine only one euro. Not two, or five. One! Why? Because –– and please excuse my French –– the machine is a whore! It will take your change and not give it back. So if you want coffee before you walk, give it only one euro please. Unless you like losing your money.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laughter fills the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One more thing. Listen. For many of you, this is your first Camino. You will get blisters. You will feel pain. You will have days when you want to cry, give up, and go home. But don’t. The Camino will provide for you and care for you. Surrender to it. It will give you everything you need –– but not always everything you want, eh? There’s a difference. Trust the Camino. Listen to it. Have faith in it. Let it guide you. Surrender to the way.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ok. So who’s ready to check in?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/begin.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
      <item>
        <title>0: Introduction</title>
        <link>/posts/introduction/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <author>Phil Nguyen</author>
        <guid>/posts/introduction/</guid>
        <description>

&lt;p&gt;In May of 2017, while working in a Title I Elementary school in New Hampshire, I read a little fable called “Rebirth” by Kaval Ravikant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main character, Amit, is unable to return home after the death of his estranged father. He wanders, lost and filled with pain and grief, and is led to the Camino de Santiago. There he meets many travelers and pilgrims. Some are lost and searching for answers, others are running from their past, but all have a story to share. Along the month-long journey, he is faced with the big questions of life, causing him to grow in a new direction and way of being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon finishing the story, the seeds of the Camino were planted in my mind. &amp;ldquo;I will walk the Camino one day,&amp;rdquo; I thought. And perhaps by fate, just when I needed them to bloom, the seeds came to fruition 3 months later at a summer camp in Maine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summer-camp-maine&#34;&gt;Summer Camp, Maine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had just finished my year of service with City Year, New Hampshire. The plan afterwards was to attend Boston University for a graduate program in Educational Leadership and Policy Studies. But it didn’t feel like a good fit for me, so I withdrew my application and, with little time for decisions and no alternatives in sight, took a job as a camp counselor in Maine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the second week of camp I applied for a job in Colorado, confident of my ability to secure the position. But I was only met by dey rejection. It then become clear to me that I had no sense of direction in my life. I had nearly accepted an offer to go to graduate school only because it seemed like the proper thing to do, and I had applied to a random job in Colorado because I yearned for a sense of security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what was I truly willing to work for? What did I actually want to do with my life? How did I want to live? These questions haunted me, beckoning for some resolution, yet I had no answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I turned to books for guidance––my usual coping strategy––and reread The Alchemist and When Breath Becomes Air. The Alchemist inspired a dreamy sense of possibility while Breath instilled a demanding sense of urgency. But neither resolved my growing existential angst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later, like a godsend, the idea of walking the Camino came to mind. The sensible me thought the idea was impulsive and irresponsible: what if I was wasting my time? Was I only avoiding my problems? Was I simply choosing to run away? In the end my gut ignored these worries and made the decision for me: I went to the farmhouse&amp;ndash;the only place with internet access at camp&amp;ndash;and bought a one-way ticket to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strange thing happened once my mind had settled on the decision: life got better. Once I had finally committed to something, my capacity to experience grew as I settled into the present. Camp became a pure source of joy, my relationships improved, my worries tempered. I reveled in the interplay of Maine’s idyllic landscapes, the slow passage of time, and the high-pitched screams of happy campers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one of our last nights off, some of the Hungarian staff and I decided to camp in Acadia National Park. We pitched our tents beneath an array of stars and pine silhouettes, lit a fire, and feasted on chips, beer, and wine. The smell of sizzling bacon and campfire filled the air. I turned toward my foreign friends, then to the grand night sky. In that moment, it felt as if the universe was watching over me. I entrusted my future to it, I believed that everything would work itself out, I let go of the incessant desire to control everything. In the warm arms of the sublime, I felt light, free, happy, and loved. Like Charlie from The Perks of Being a Wallflower, I felt infinite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/camp-kiddo.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;me and a kiddo&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-woods-of-maine&#34;&gt;The Woods of Maine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the last day of camp, I paddled out to the middle of Echo Lake and sat amid the glossy water, wondering what to make of the whole experience, contemplating how the future would unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my birthday –– August 10th. &amp;ldquo;Not much has changed but me,&amp;rdquo; I thought. &amp;ldquo;I am the same person as I was yesterday, only now I will walk around with the number 24 plastered to my identity.&amp;rdquo; I was no longer 23, 15, or 10. Yet in a sense, I was: I was still the flippant adolescent of 14, the bashful child of 7, the confused adult of 18 to 23. How was I to define 24?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote a promise to myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This life you have before you is the only certainty. Don’t take it for granted. Own it and live it with meaning, beauty, courage, grace, and presence. Dare to dream. Spend it with people you love, spend it loving people. Be heartbroken, be brave, make mistakes. Do all of the things that scare the shit out of you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/camp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once camp ended, I drove down to New Hampshire to see an old friend. We hiked Mount Washington –– I was barefoot –– and exchanged stories in the backdrop of the White Mountains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I camped in the woods of Maine for five days while waiting for my friend Eszter to finish her remaining days at camp. In the woods, I saw my inner demons with staggering clarity. Insecurity, self-doubt, fear, loneliness –– they had settled themselves nicely in the forefront of my being. It was only when I had learned to accept them as parts of me was I able to enjoy nature’s invitation to solitude and serenity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One night, sitting on the crest of Seboeis Lake, I watched the clear water shimmer, and a growing sense of calm began to overtake me. My problems grew small, insignificant, and petty, fading altogether as the water reposed and sun descended. Silence took its hold and my perception of time disappeared. It was incredibly peaceful, and I started to cry and laugh out of sheer euphoria. My audience, an ensemble of crickets, cicadas and other creatures, echoed in unison under the starry sky. I had been invited to witness a crescendo of grand proportions, and nature was the composer. My loneliness, for a moment, was alleviated, and the words of Oliver Sacks rang through my mind: I, then and there, in the middle of an intimate intercourse with the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moments like these were rare. I recognized they were more likely to visit in conditions that allow for total stillness. Should a person survive what initially feels like a trial by fire, this staggering state of loneliness, they emerge more alive and deeply in-tune with the world around them. Their capacity for love, understanding, and presence deepens. They become infinitely more capable. They are grateful to have been called back as cast members in the grand play of the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;canada&#34;&gt;Canada&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met Eszter in a canoe. Initially she seemed hesitant to tag along because she either didn’t know how to swim, or she couldn’t swim very well. Regardless, in an attempt to ease her concerned look&amp;ndash;and probably to impress her&amp;ndash;I assured her that I had done this before, that she could trust me to take her safely across the vast Echo Lake. In truth, it was my first time ever commanding a canoe. Luckily for the both of us, it turned out to be a relatively easy task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summer air was pristine, the lake gleamed in the sunlight, loon calls echoed in the distance. It was a perfect afternoon. I took notice of Eszter’s dark eyes, her rough European accent, her curious necklace with a dragon hanging from it. She came from Hungary and worked in the Chef Camp program. We talked about nature and our place as humans in it, what life at camp was like, our lives outside of camp, U.S. consumerism, among other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t see each other again until weeks later. Camp kept us busy, I out on the lake and she in the corners of Chef Camp. A few days after I had decided to walk the Camino, she posted on the camp Facebook page that she was looking for people to go to Canada with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point I had developed a crush on her, which, to me, seemed terribly irrational. She lived in Hungary, English wasn’t her native language, and I had no clue as to what I would be doing for the rest of the year. Regardless, the feelings were there, and I wanted to be in her company. What did I have to lose? At the very least, the trip would be fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, we met and talked about the trip. We considered flying to Quebec and Montreal, but that meant I would&amp;rsquo;ve needed to find a place to store my car –– more unnecessary expenditures. So I offered to drive instead. She looked at me with excited, perhaps bewildered eyes and said, in her rough Hungarian accent, “We’re going to fucking Canada!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two days we drove from Maine to Quebec, from Quebec to Montreal, and from Montreal to Niagara Falls, with some detours to Ottawa and Cobourg in-between. Our friendship grew through the confluence of stupid jokes and cringy puns, camper stories, and Hungarian metal. She taught me Hungarian curse words and I taught her American colloquialisms. Stuff like &amp;ldquo;brooo, suhp duuude, liike, y’know.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What brought us close was our willingness to be vulnerable: we were open, honest, and non-judgmental in sharing our pasts, in telling each other our worst fears and deepest worries. We exchanged secrets that possessed the capacity to destroy a person, secrets and thoughts that most people hide and bury in their psyches for eternity. Yet there we were, two people who were once complete strangers, attempting to piece together the incomplete shards of our disparate pasts, constructing the foundation of an enduring friendship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In moments like these, I wanted to pull her close, wrap her in my arms, and tell her that everything would be fine&amp;ndash;that everything was fine, at least for the moment; that even if I did not fully understand her situation, I would always be there for her; that we, with our powers combined, could get through anything; that she was with me, the overly optimistic, boundlessly romantic, Phil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We parted ways at Toronto Pearson International Airport. She was heading to Mexico, and I to Ohio. It was a bittersweet goodbye&amp;ndash;bitter because I have never been good at letting people go despite all of the practice I&amp;rsquo;ve had, sweet because I had been lucky enough to have shared the journey with her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She told me, as we let one another out of our embrace, &amp;ldquo;Phil, it not a goodbye. It&amp;rsquo;s a see you later.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;departure-to-the-camino-september-5th-2017&#34;&gt;Departure to the Camino: September 5th, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke up in Boston on the cold, wooden floor of my friend’s apartment. It was his first day of graduate school, and my last in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only possessions were my 30L backpack, three sets of outfits, two books, a sleeping bag, my down jacket, a phone charger, toiletries, my boots, and a 12-pack of granola bars. My pack weighed no more than 10 lbs. The only thing left to prepare was my mind. I was jittery and nervous, but also breathless and excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent most of the morning in a coffee shop writing a letter to my friends:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My life on the move is far from over: tonight, I will fly to Europe to begin my journey on the Camino de Santiago, a 500 mile trek across Northern Spain. It will take me 33-35 days to complete. And while I intend to do it alone, it will not be a solitary experience; I expect to meet and travel with people of all ages and walks of life on the road to Santiago. The Camino is one of my lifelong goals, and the opportunity to do it could be no more prime than now.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My motivations are simple: I want to see the world. I want to grow. I want to do something that scares the shit out of me.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the pursuit of dreams, dreamers are met with several challenges. In my case, it was always figuring out what my next step was, dealing with the incessant self-doubt and fear that accompanies the process, and letting go of the attachments I developed with people, comfort, and calcified ideas that no longer served me. Such is the nature of walking the less trodden path. It’s unpaved, rocky, and dissuasive. If you don’t watch your step, you might just slip.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, in the words of Robert Frost, “[taking] the [road] less traveled by, / that has made all the difference”, the difference being a profound learning experience, a life lived on your own terms, a dream turned concrete reality.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, in a nutshell, is where I am going. You’ll know when I have made it across. Thanks for the love and support.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Sincerity and Gratitude,&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your friendly neighbor, Phil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After posting the update to Facebook, I thought of my parents and the argument we had a few days prior about my decision to walk the Camino. They believed I was being reckless, that I should’ve taken the opportunity at Boston University. They believed that I, at the age of 24, should&amp;rsquo;ve had my life figured out. I felt like a disappointment, a terrible son. But this was the path I had decided to walk, and I needed them to know that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t backing out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote a journal entry expressing my frustrations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About the world, about my place, &lt;br&gt;
About where I belong &lt;br&gt;
In this infinite space, &lt;br&gt;
I sit at the margin, misunderstood. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collide and tear each other apart &lt;br&gt;
What ever happened to our graceful start? &lt;br&gt;
I a child, &lt;br&gt;
You unconditional. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want understanding – I want love. &lt;br&gt;
Forgive me and my trespasses&lt;br&gt;
As I learn how to forgive myself,&lt;br&gt;
And love you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I wrote them a letter expressing how I felt. I sent it minutes before boarding the plane to Europe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear Mom and Dad,&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past twenty or so years, you have given me the best gift a child can ask for: your unconditional love. Despite our conflicts, despite our differences, despite the ever-growing physical distance between us, you have loved and supported me unflinchingly. Thank you for that.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worlds you and I grew up in could be no more different. I was born and raised in the safe and sunny suburbs of California; you in the dangerous aftermath of the Vietnam war. My childhood consisted of friendships, books, and video games; yours of rice fields, conflict, and uncertainty. Where I see possibility, you see risk. I struggle to know what’s next, who I will become; you struggled to survive.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand why you might feel the way you do about the path I currently walk – certainly scared, frustrated, saddened, uncomfortable, and maybe even disappointed. But know that you have raised a son who is strong, kind, independent, adventurous, curious, passionate, and happy. You have raised someone who isn&amp;rsquo;t afraid to chase after what he wants, after what he dreams of. Most importantly, you have taught me the meaning of compassion and kindness; that it isn&amp;rsquo;t always what we say that&amp;rsquo;s important, but what we do instead.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ever meet the people I&amp;rsquo;ve had the fortune of developing relationships with, I think they would say I am an easygoing, thoughtful, caring, friendly, loyal, and loving person; that I would give them the shirt off of my back and the food on my table to make them feel loved and welcomed. I only have you two to thank for this. You have taught me to be a person of good character; you have given me the basic necessities for leading a fulfilled and meaningful life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as I step out into the world and begin to draw my own map of it, I need your love more than ever. Because I will stumble and fall; I will get hurt and be heartbroken; I will be sad and frustrated and challenged beyond anything I have yet to face in my one and short life. But what&amp;rsquo;s life worth anyways if I don&amp;rsquo;t risk getting scratched and bruised along the way? That&amp;rsquo;s just a part of growing up; that’s how I have grown up; that&amp;rsquo;s how I want to grow up.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re scared I won&amp;rsquo;t continue my &amp;ldquo;education&amp;rdquo;, don&amp;rsquo;t worry: my education has never been limited to the confines of a classroom. Life itself is the greatest teacher, and I am taught something new everyday.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you worry I am a loose-cannon with no bearings or a home: Home has never been about a location or house. Home is where you feel at home, and for me, that is when I am growing. I am currently expanding the home of my heart.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever it is that drives me forward will continue to do so. That&amp;rsquo;s not to say this force is inflexible or incapable of change, but rather that I will not deviate from who I am and becoming. All I ask is for your continued love and acceptance of me. All of me. Not of who you wish me to be, but of who I already am.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask of myself to do the same. To accept and love you as you are and who you will become throughout time and eternity. I am endlessly grateful.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love,&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Son&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sending it was one of the hardest things I have ever done. I was petrified &amp;ndash; what would they say? Would they even understand? We weren’t a family that expressed our feelings so openly like this. It was always about the basics &amp;ndash; food, water, money, school, family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before boarding, my Mom left me with this message:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Philip, remember you will always be our son. I know you’re independent and want to do what you want, but always remember that. Me and your Dad will always support you, but know that I don’t feel happy about what you’re doing. I don’t feel good. I’m scared. Please stay safe. Keep us updated and send pictures. Your Dad and I love you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heartbroken? Swelling with love? Check and check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we ever truly ready for the future? I don’t think so. Life is too uncertain to always be prepared for it. But that shouldn’t deter us from living fully. Whether or not we have fun in the process is a choice. Me? I chose to dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I boarded the plane, unsure of what was to come. In the air, I took one last look at the Boston skyline, the clouds pressed against the horizon. A brilliant swath of pinkish-orange hues left the sky ablaze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind me rested home. Ahead, answers amid a foreign landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/../photos/shoes.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      
    
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
