<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phil in the Blank</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Phil in the Blank</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 21:48:51 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>In a Nutshell</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 21:48:51 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi I’m Phil. Currently I help run the ABCD Study in Vermont.
Prior I worked in a mental health and addiction treatment center, a Title I elementary school in New Hampshire, and an 8-week overnight summer camp in Maine.
Books, people, playing outside, and learning bring me joy.
California native turned New England enthusiast.
I walked across Spain once and wrote about it.
The Site &amp;lsquo;Phil in the Blank&amp;rsquo; is my ongoing attempt at making sense of the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rome</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-06-23-rome/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-06-23-rome/</guid>
      <description>I recently went to Rome, and it was nothing short of stimulating, sensuous, and overwhelming. From the minimal use of ingredients in Italian cuisine to the incredible works of Michaelangelo and other Roman artists, everywhere you went, everything you touched, tasted and smelled, everything you experienced, it all seemed like some part of a grand plan aimed at steering one’s senses toward a deeper appreciation and understanding of beauty and aesthetics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bearing Witness</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-06-07-bearing-witness/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-06-07-bearing-witness/</guid>
      <description>There were 16 of us nestled in the sunlit alcove of the church. I looked at the stranger sitting on a navy-blue cushion before me and wondered what she was thinking about. She smiled at me, and I smiled back. We introduced ourselves and made small talk, as did everyone else and their adjacent stranger. Then the bell chimed, and the room fell into silence.
We turned our gaze to Mike, the PI of the study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Pale Blue Dot</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-03-15-pale-blue-dot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-03-15-pale-blue-dot/</guid>
      <description>Propelled into space in 1977, NASA’s scientific objective of launching the Voyager I was to photograph the planets of the outer solar system. They expected the spacecraft to function no further than Saturn. Yet work it did, and it continues to defy expectation up to this day, still traveling at 40,000 miles per hour, somewhere at or beyond the edges of our solar system.
When the Voyager passed Saturn, Carl Sagan – astronomer, cosmologist, astrophysicist, lover and communicator of science – requested that NASA turn the cameras back toward home.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shoreless Seeds and Stardust</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-03-12-shoreless-seeds-and-stardust/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-03-12-shoreless-seeds-and-stardust/</guid>
      <description>I ventured out onto the lake today, this time beyond the frozen crest that marks the boundary between bay and lake, contemplating the last line of Maria Popova’s Figuring: “What will survive of us are shoreless seeds and stardust.” My saunter figured into a sprint as the mountains came into view, and soon the voices behind me were no more than whispers. Minutes later I ran into a couple playing in the snow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons in Adulthood</title>
      <link>/posts/adulthood/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/adulthood/</guid>
      <description>Crossroads My year of service with City Year, New Hampshire was coming to an end. I knew that I didn’t want to become a teacher anymore, but I still liked the idea of shaping the young minds of the future, so I applied to Boston University’s Masters program in Educational Leadership and Policy Studies.
I was waiting for my flight home in O’Hare International Airport when I received the news.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mary Oliver</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-01-19-mary-oliver/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-01-19-mary-oliver/</guid>
      <description>We first met in the biting winter nights of my service year in New Hampshire. I listened with full attention as she illuminated the nuances and contours of the world through the written word, hers, words that continue to remind me I am never truly alone, words that continue to show me the world is always at offer to the playground of my imagination.
Later, when faced with the task of figuring what direction my life should go, she visited me in Spain and reminded me not to worry, that things will take the time they take, that even Saint Augustine followed many roads before he became Saint Augustine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Letters to a Young Scientist</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-08-05-letters-to-a-young-scientist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-08-05-letters-to-a-young-scientist/</guid>
      <description>Veteran biologist and teacher of science Edward Wilson lays out a few principles for the young scientist to keep in mind as he/she/they proceed in their career:
 Put passion ahead of training. Feel out in any way you can what you most want to do in science, or technology, or some other science-related profession. Obey that passion as long as it lasts. Feed it with the knowledge the mind needs to grow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serendipity</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-17-serendipity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-17-serendipity/</guid>
      <description>We sift through life without any compasses to guide us through the messy unknown, like aimless treasure hunters searching for diamonds in the dark.
The unknown scares us. We&amp;rsquo;re not so comfortable immersed in this infinite expanse. Maybe this is why the human brain has evolved the ability to construe stories from unrelated anecdotes and scattered tidbits: we find comfort in connecting the dots, we tell ourselves everything happens for a reason.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winter</title>
      <link>/posts/winter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/winter/</guid>
      <description>Arbiter of cessation, master of endings, a gust inevitably endured. Clench your jaw now, the exchange is complete: Snow and frost for people and sidewalks. Inches and burdens for sauntered footfalls.
There is a season between seasons a bridge that is crossed by the plentiful few. Adults and scientists seek it endlessly though only the children know of its whereabouts. But don’t bother with asking–– they’re sworn to the promises of secrecy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forgiveness</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-09-forgiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-09-forgiveness/</guid>
      <description>Forgiveness moves us toward a better future by inviting us to look at the past, at the unrelenting, painful ghosts that continue to permeate and darken every corner of our lives.
Sometimes we need to feel rage, to tussle with guilt, to fall into our sorrows before we can forgive. No, forgiveness is not about avoiding these emotions. Rather, forgiveness asks us to show up daily with unwavering courage, compassion, receptivity, and kindness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feelings</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-06-feelings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-06-feelings/</guid>
      <description>Feelings are fleeting by nature, like the passage of clouds on a warm summer day.
Though too often we wear them like immutable masks and declare, &amp;ldquo;This is me. This is all I will ever be.&amp;rdquo; Sad. Resentful. Despondent. Happy. In truth they are masks, transient facades that hide a more true and vulnerable sense of self.
We put these masks on when we&amp;rsquo;re scared, when we&amp;rsquo;re too afraid to ask for attention and love; when we&amp;rsquo;re on the verge of breaking, but don&amp;rsquo;t know how to ask for help.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Love Letter</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-02-love-letter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-02-love-letter/</guid>
      <description>Dear stranger, I know we’ve just met but, I love you.
I love you more than you could know. I love you unconditionally. I love you.
I cannot know your pain, your experience, Your suffering. That is all yours. But you do not have to bear it alone.
Dance with melancholy And sing out your blues but please Don&amp;rsquo;t stop.
Talk to me. Tell me about it. Whatever you feel, feel it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18: Home</title>
      <link>/posts/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/home/</guid>
      <description>After Belgium, I spent one night in Prague and took a bus to Hungary the next morning. I stayed in Budapest for 10 days with Eszter, the Hungarian woman I had a crush on at the beginning of this whole adventure.
It felt strange, to be back in the swing of normalcy, as if such a thing was possible after such a journey.
There was no bitterness or resentment toward Marieke.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>17: The Final Goodbye</title>
      <link>/posts/final-goodbye/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/final-goodbye/</guid>
      <description>I arrive in Belgium late in the afternoon. The weather is exceptional: half-clouded skies with no reservation of sunlight, a perfect balance of cool and warm. I exit from the train station and hoist myself against a tall statue, eagerly looking for my squirrelly Belgium. 15 minutes pass before I spot her standing only 20 meters behind me, clad in a gray hoodie and a black leather jacket, lightly faded jeans and the tall leather boots of an amazon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>16: Santiago</title>
      <link>/posts/santiago/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/santiago/</guid>
      <description>“How we spend our days is, of course, how we spend our lives.” –Annie Dillard
 October 8, 2017 - Day 31 Pedrouzo, Spain.
In 20 kilometers, I will reach Santiago de Compostela. The anticipation has left me sleepless. Ali and Karen are fast asleep. Hope to see them again soon. I pack my things and make a quiet exit.
It’s dark out. Cars lie dormant under the hazy hue of flickering streetlights.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15: Letters Worth Czeching Out</title>
      <link>/posts/letters-czech/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/letters-czech/</guid>
      <description>I wrote these letters to my friend, Stepan, from the Czech Republic. Including them because they might help to create a better picture of my experience. He had joined M and I a few days before M left. These letters were written afterwards.
September 23, 2017  Hey it&amp;rsquo;s Phil.
I walked to Hontanas yesterday from Burgos (about 30 km). It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful village worth staying at. Today I&amp;rsquo;m walking to Itero de Vega, about 21 km.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14: Letters to a Camino Soulmate</title>
      <link>/posts/letters-soulmate/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/letters-soulmate/</guid>
      <description>These are the emails Marieke and I wrote to each other after she was gone. They might give you a better picture of my Camino experience. Writing to her was always a highlight. Sorry for the grammar. Wrote every letter on my phone.
September 21, 2017  I just realized I did not give you my email. Safe travels! Thank you for everything.
–Phil
 September 23, 2017  Yesterday, as I walked away from Burgos, it clicked: you were gone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13: The Iron Cross</title>
      <link>/posts/ironcross/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ironcross/</guid>
      <description>October 1st, 2017 - Day 25 Dawn. A ridge of silhouettes and gray clouds against a colorless expanse. A string of headlamps clambering up a mountain. At the top, an iron cross.
The autumnal air invigorates me, my legs are weightless. I pass several pilgrims on my way up. Shanti is up ahead. I reach him and he smiles at me. We climb through the dark together, delighting in the thrill of the ascent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12: Journal Entries from Day 22 - 24</title>
      <link>/posts/journal22-24/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/journal22-24/</guid>
      <description>September 28, 2017 - Day 22 To be yourself–
Easy to say, hard to do.
What we think is not ours.
What we believe is shaped by others.
The only thing we own is
what we feel.
Our inner compass, the way we connect with
The outer world; only we can see and touch and
Feel the way we do. Never lose it.
Never let it go.

Met Enrico and Sia today.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11: A Sea of Stars</title>
      <link>/posts/stars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/stars/</guid>
      <description>Day 21 4:30am. I inch out from my sleeping bag like a slug, careful not to disturb the others in the room, pack my things and head downstairs. Pauline and Morgan are already awake. We’re late.
My eyes are crusty. I wolf down a prepacked sandwich – chorizo and cheese – with yogurt. Pauline makes us some coffee. Bland, but it will do. Shoes on, rucksacks shouldered, we’re on the move.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10: Journal Entries from Day 17 - 20</title>
      <link>/posts/journal17-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/journal17-20/</guid>
      <description>September 23, 2017 - Day 17 We are always on the cusp of collapse and redemption. Do we choose to rise, or do we settle and fall?
Stories = meaning. The mind is a meaning-making machine.
Stories have the power to change people’s lives, and we are the narrators.

Today, a group of Americans invited me to their table at dinner. They were much older than me and asked a lot of questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9: An Ode to the Road</title>
      <link>/posts/ode/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/ode/</guid>
      <description>Each and every day I wake and walk with the sun.
It starts low, climbing over hillsides, rising slowly.
It finds its temporary place amid the sky
and begins to color the Meseta.
Front and center a shadow grows.
It looks at me with indifference – a mirror of my darker side.
Fear, insecurity, doubt,
The manifestation of my inner demons.
Each and every day, I wake and walk and confront them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8: Gone</title>
      <link>/posts/gone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/gone/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve sunken into the depths of an all-too-familiar melancholy.
She is gone. I am alone. My emotions swing to the erratic cadence of an unforgiving metronome.
 I’m fine. Tick. I’m fine. Tick. I’m not. Tick. 
I miss the jade of her eyes, those luminescent opals I so often lose myself in. The ease of her smile, always able to bring about my own. The way she plucked those juicy blackberries from their thorny brambles, always a tad out of reach, the hem of her shirt lifting ever so slightly in the process, revealing the contours of a titillating landscape I secretly wished to explore.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7: Goodbye</title>
      <link>/posts/goodbye/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/goodbye/</guid>
      <description>Day 15. We’re sitting amid a small cluster of dining tables in the main plaza of Burgos, sipping on wine and eating tapas. The patrons and pilgrims look happy, the cathedral towers above us. I look up and wonder, is there such a thing as a good goodbye?
Marieke looks content and tells her squirrel joke again. I try to listen, but my attention has been seized by the fact that she is leaving tonight.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6: Sunsets and Soulmates</title>
      <link>/posts/suns-souls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/suns-souls/</guid>
      <description>“Phil! I have a genius idea. You’re really going to like it.”
It&amp;rsquo;s the 12th day. Marieke, Stepan and I go to the top of a hill to catch the sunset. We sift through an amber field of grass and wheat and settle ourselves in a small circular clearing. The sky is cloudless, a cool breeze is present.
We talk for awhile, about what I cant&amp;rsquo;t remember, but I feel wonderfully content.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5: The Cusp of Time and Infinity</title>
      <link>/posts/cusp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/cusp/</guid>
      <description>In the morning we walk to Pamplona, our first city. I run into Maria and chat with her for a brief moment before running off with the girls to get breakfast. I didn’t know it then, but that would be my final conversation with her. One thing the Camino teaches you, by nature of necessity, is how to let go. People, places, your past. The present demands it be so.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4: Möge die Straße</title>
      <link>/posts/strasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/strasse/</guid>
      <description>Another gray and rainy day. We sleep in and start walking at 8am. After the deep and enlightening conversations of yesterday, we decide to walk in solitude –– together, but left to the vicinity of our inner worlds.
My feelings throughout the morning are in contrast with the highs of the previous; I was in a blue, melancholic state of mind. Thoughts of the future, about something out of reach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3: Tea</title>
      <link>/posts/tea/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/tea/</guid>
      <description>Through the window I see Sun-bathed flowers and untouched rock,
Blades of grass and untrodden walks,
Endless possibility.
I ask of you Time
To yield your determined hand
So I may dance
Forever with Infinity.
 I run into Matilde and Franca while departing from Roncesvalles. They&amp;rsquo;re headed in the opposite direction, back toward the albergue, when they call out to me.
“Phiiiiilll! Heeeey we’re gonna make some tea! Would you like to join us?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2: First Ascent</title>
      <link>/posts/firstascent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/firstascent/</guid>
      <description>I woke to the sound of creaking bunk beds, rustling backpacks, and hushed chatter. 5:30 a.m. Time to go. I put my boots on, packed my sleeping bag, and went downstairs.
Small talk of good weather and stellar walking conditions and free bread as stiff as stones. I devour as much of it as my mouth can muster and head out.
The first day was supposed to be arduous: 27 kilometers from Saint-Jean to Roncesvalles, with a gradual gain of 1400 meters in elevation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1: Beginnings</title>
      <link>/posts/beginnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/beginnings/</guid>
      <description>The Camino de Santiago is a network of pilgrimage routes that ultimately converge on the city of Santiago de Compostela in Northwestern Spain, where the great Saint James is rumored to be buried.
The most popular route is the Camino Frances. It begins at Saint-Jean-Pied-de-Port in Southern France, a small city located north of the Pyrenees, and totals about 500 miles across Spain to the city of Santiago de Compostela. Many walk the Camino for spiritual and religious reasons; I walked in search of myself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>0: Introduction</title>
      <link>/posts/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/introduction/</guid>
      <description>In May of 2017, while working in a Title I Elementary school in New Hampshire, I read a little fable called “Rebirth” by Kaval Ravikant.
The main character, Amit, is unable to return home after the death of his estranged father. He wanders, lost and filled with pain and grief, and is led to the Camino de Santiago. There he meets many travelers and pilgrims. Some are lost and searching for answers, others are running from their past, but all have a story to share.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>