<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sentiments on Phil in the Blank</title>
    <link>/tags/sentiments/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sentiments on Phil in the Blank</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/sentiments/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Shoreless Seeds and Stardust</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-03-12-shoreless-seeds-and-stardust/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-03-12-shoreless-seeds-and-stardust/</guid>
      <description>I ventured out onto the lake today, this time beyond the frozen crest that marks the boundary between bay and lake, contemplating the last line of Maria Popova’s Figuring: “What will survive of us are shoreless seeds and stardust.” My saunter figured into a sprint as the mountains came into view, and soon the voices behind me were no more than whispers. Minutes later I ran into a couple playing in the snow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mary Oliver</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-01-19-mary-oliver/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-01-19-mary-oliver/</guid>
      <description>We first met in the biting winter nights of my service year in New Hampshire. I listened with full attention as she illuminated the nuances and contours of the world through the written word, hers, words that continue to remind me I am never truly alone, words that continue to show me the world is always at offer to the playground of my imagination.
Later, when faced with the task of figuring what direction my life should go, she visited me in Spain and reminded me not to worry, that things will take the time they take, that even Saint Augustine followed many roads before he became Saint Augustine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serendipity</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-17-serendipity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-17-serendipity/</guid>
      <description>We sift through life without any compasses to guide us through the messy unknown, like aimless treasure hunters searching for diamonds in the dark.
The unknown scares us. We&amp;rsquo;re not so comfortable immersed in this infinite expanse. Maybe this is why the human brain has evolved the ability to construe stories from unrelated anecdotes and scattered tidbits: we find comfort in connecting the dots, we tell ourselves everything happens for a reason.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Winter</title>
      <link>/posts/winter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/winter/</guid>
      <description>Arbiter of cessation, master of endings, a gust inevitably endured. Clench your jaw now, the exchange is complete: Snow and frost for people and sidewalks. Inches and burdens for sauntered footfalls.
There is a season between seasons a bridge that is crossed by the plentiful few. Adults and scientists seek it endlessly though only the children know of its whereabouts. But don’t bother with asking–– they’re sworn to the promises of secrecy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forgiveness</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-09-forgiveness/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-09-forgiveness/</guid>
      <description>Forgiveness moves us toward a better future by inviting us to look at the past, at the unrelenting, painful ghosts that continue to permeate and darken every corner of our lives.
Sometimes we need to feel rage, to tussle with guilt, to fall into our sorrows before we can forgive. No, forgiveness is not about avoiding these emotions. Rather, forgiveness asks us to show up daily with unwavering courage, compassion, receptivity, and kindness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Feelings</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-06-feelings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-06-feelings/</guid>
      <description>Feelings are fleeting by nature, like the passage of clouds on a warm summer day.
Though too often we wear them like immutable masks and declare, &amp;ldquo;This is me. This is all I will ever be.&amp;rdquo; Sad. Resentful. Despondent. Happy. In truth they are masks, transient facades that hide a more true and vulnerable sense of self.
We put these masks on when we&amp;rsquo;re scared, when we&amp;rsquo;re too afraid to ask for attention and love; when we&amp;rsquo;re on the verge of breaking, but don&amp;rsquo;t know how to ask for help.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Love Letter</title>
      <link>/posts/2018-01-02-love-letter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2018-01-02-love-letter/</guid>
      <description>Dear stranger, I know we’ve just met but, I love you.
I love you more than you could know. I love you unconditionally. I love you.
I cannot know your pain, your experience, Your suffering. That is all yours. But you do not have to bear it alone.
Dance with melancholy And sing out your blues but please Don&amp;rsquo;t stop.
Talk to me. Tell me about it. Whatever you feel, feel it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>